<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:version="2.0"><channel><title>bakeery 🧊</title><description>A blog template</description><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/</link><language>en</language><item><title>How to Safely Access the Dark Web and Gather Information Securely</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/access-darkweb/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/access-darkweb/</guid><description>This guide provides essential tips on how to safely access the dark web and gather information while ensuring privacy and security</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/access-darkweb/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/access-darkweb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Warning&gt;
  **Caution:** Accessing the dark web can expose you to illegal activities, cyber threats, and dangerous content. Always take proper security precautions, use secure browsing methods (e.g., Tor, VPNs), and ensure you are abiding by all applicable laws and regulations. This guide is for informational purposes only and should not be used for unlawful activities.
&lt;/Warning&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Introduction to DarkWeb&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dark web is a hidden part of the internet that is not indexed by traditional search engines like Google or Bing. It exists within a network known as the Deep Web, which is made up of sites that are not accessible through regular browsing. To access the dark web, users typically use specialized tools like Tor (The Onion Router), which anonymizes internet traffic, ensuring privacy and security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the dark web can be a haven for privacy-conscious users, it is also notorious for hosting illegal activities such as the sale of drugs, weapons, and stolen data. Due to its anonymous nature, the dark web offers a space for individuals to communicate and share information without the risk of surveillance. However, it’s important to exercise extreme caution when exploring this part of the internet, as it can expose users to significant cybersecurity risk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tools We Will Use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Linux Machine (Remux)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;A secure and isolated environment for accessing the dark web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Brave Browser&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;A privacy-focused browser that offers enhanced security features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;KeePass Password Manager&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;A reliable tool for managing and securing passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProtonVPN&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;A trustworthy VPN to protect your anonymity and encrypt your connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;ProtonMail&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br&gt;A secure, encrypted email service for anonymous communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had several questions from friends and classmates on how to access the dark web securely, and I realized that many of them have no idea how to do it safely. While it’s not illegal to access the dark web, one must be extra careful. Let&amp;#39;s get started...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Installation of Remux&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, ensure that you have a &lt;strong&gt;hypervisor&lt;/strong&gt; installed. This can be VirtualBox, VMware, or any other virtual machine software. For this tutorial, we will be using &lt;strong&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/strong&gt;. You can download it from the official website:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.virtualbox.org/wiki/Downloads&quot;&gt;Download VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we’ll install &lt;strong&gt;Remux&lt;/strong&gt;. To do this, visit the official website to download the &lt;strong&gt;.ova&lt;/strong&gt; file:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.remnux.org/install-distro/get-virtual-appliance&quot;&gt;Download Remux Virtual Appliance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the download is complete, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open VirtualBox and go to &lt;strong&gt;File&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Import Appliance&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the folder icon to locate and select the &lt;strong&gt;.ova&lt;/strong&gt; file you just downloaded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Start&lt;/strong&gt; to begin the import process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for the virtual machine to boot up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there you have it! You now have a fresh installation of &lt;strong&gt;Remux&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Installation of brave browser&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instruction on how to download Brave Browser can be found on Brave official website &lt;a href=&quot;https://brave.com/en-in/linux/&quot;&gt;Download Brave Browser&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo apt install curl

sudo curl -fsSLo /usr/share/keyrings/brave-browser-archive-keyring.gpg https://brave-browser-apt-release.s3.brave.com/brave-browser-archive-keyring.gpg

echo &amp;quot;deb [signed-by=/usr/share/keyrings/brave-browser-archive-keyring.gpg] https://brave-browser-apt-release.s3.brave.com/ stable main&amp;quot;|sudo tee /etc/apt/sources.list.d/brave-browser-release.list

sudo apt update

sudo apt install brave-browser
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install KeePass Password Manager&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KeePass is a great password manager that we&amp;#39;ll use to securely store &lt;strong&gt;onion links&lt;/strong&gt;, as well as &lt;strong&gt;credentials&lt;/strong&gt; for marketplaces and forums. It&amp;#39;s a good idea to have everything organized and managed in one place, making it easy to access later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install KeePass on your system, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update your package list and Install KeePass&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo apt update
sudo apt install keepass2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the installation is complete, launch KeePass and create your master key to log into the password manager. This will serve as your main access point for securely managing your passwords and sensitive information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation and Setting up of VPN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I really need a VPN?, well it depends 
Using a VPN with the Tor network is often suggested for added privacy, but it’s not always necessary and could introduce risks. Here’s why:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When to Use a VPN&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your ISP blocks Tor traffic or monitors your internet usage:
A VPN can mask your activity from the ISP and allow you to access Tor.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your ISP doesn’t restrict Tor:
Using Tor directly is safer and avoids adding unnecessary layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Risks of Using a VPN&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trust Shift:
A VPN hides your activity from your ISP but makes the VPN provider a potential point of trust. If the VPN logs your data, it could be misused or exposed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Decrypted Traffic Risk:
Before your data enters the Tor network, it passes through the VPN server. If your traffic is not encrypted (e.g., HTTP instead of HTTPS), it can be viewed or logged by the VPN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tor’s Built-In Privacy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tor anonymizes traffic by routing it through multiple encrypted layers (nodes).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your real IP is only visible to the first node (entry node).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Tor directly eliminates the risk of VPN providers logging your data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Best Practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only use a VPN if necessary and choose one with a strict no-logs policy.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always verify that websites use &lt;em&gt;HTTPS&lt;/em&gt; to protect data from exit node monitoring.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Tor directly if you don’t face ISP restrictions for optimal privacy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, while VPNs can help in specific cases, they aren’t always safer, especially if the provider is unreliable. Tor’s design already prioritizes anonymity when used correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;List of some Trusted VPN Providers for Safe Browsing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ProtonVPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;A privacy-focused VPN with a strong commitment to security and no-logs policy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://protonvpn.com&quot;&gt;Visit ProtonVPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ExpressVPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Known for its fast speeds and strong encryption, it’s widely recommended for secure browsing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.expressvpn.com&quot;&gt;Visit ExpressVPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NordVPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Offers excellent privacy features, including double encryption and a no-logs policy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nordvpn.com&quot;&gt;Visit NordVPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mullvad VPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;A privacy-centric VPN that doesn’t require any personal information for sign-up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mullvad.net&quot;&gt;Visit Mullvad VPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CyberGhost VPN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Offers a wide range of servers and is known for its robust security features and privacy commitment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cyberghostvpn.com&quot;&gt;Visit CyberGhost VPN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surfshark&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;A budget-friendly option with a strong emphasis on privacy, security, and unlimited device connections.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://surfshark.com&quot;&gt;Visit Surfshark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private Internet Access (PIA)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;A reliable VPN with strong encryption and a no-logs policy, ideal for privacy-conscious users.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privateinternetaccess.com&quot;&gt;Visit PIA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These VPNs are trusted by privacy advocates and are excellent choices when accessing the dark web or browsing securely. you can sign up on anyone of the above and get connected&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating a ProtonMail Account&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a good idea to have a secure email account for registering on services where you don’t want to reveal your real identity or if you want to communicate anonymously. ProtonMail offers a great solution for this, allowing you to protect your privacy with end-to-end encryption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can create a free anonymous email account here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://proton.me/mail&quot;&gt;Sign up for ProtonMail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want additional features, you can consider upgrading to a paid plan:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://proton.me/mail/pricing&quot;&gt;View ProtonMail Pricing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Info&gt;
  Make sure all the above-mentioned tools are installed before proceeding. Once you&apos;re ready, let&apos;s begin accessing the dark web safely and ethically.
&lt;/Info&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might know, &lt;strong&gt;onion links&lt;/strong&gt; are not easily readable or memorable. To access dark web sites, you typically need to search for collections of onion links. You can find these links on various platforms, but always keep in mind the risks involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sources to Find Onion Links:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Many repositories compile collections of onion links. It&amp;#39;s a great resource for discovering dark web websites.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fastfire/deepdarkCTI/blob/main/forum.md&quot;&gt;DeepDarkCTI Forum Links&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/5ky1ar/Awesome-Onion-Links&quot;&gt;Awesome Onion Links&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/0x00009b/8cf0c2b0e147dc0c1114fb32b5d2d7a3&quot;&gt;0x00009b/onion_links&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://2fd6cemt4gmccflhm6imvdfvli3nf7zn6rfrwpsy7uhxrgbypvwf5fad.onion/&quot;&gt; Search Engine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Telegram&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Various Telegram channels often share onion links, but be cautious as they might link to dangerous sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blogs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Several cybersecurity blogs compile lists of onion links, offering curated collections of dark web websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dark Web Itself&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Once you access the dark web, you may encounter hidden forums, directories, and search engines that list onion links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;Warning&gt;
  Dark Web Links (Caution: Accessing these links is at your own risk)

&lt;p&gt;  These links are provided for &lt;strong&gt;informational purposes only&lt;/strong&gt;. I am not responsible for the content found at these URLs. Accessing these sites may expose you to &lt;strong&gt;illegal content&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;malware&lt;/strong&gt;, and other &lt;strong&gt;security risks&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;Please exercise extreme caution.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/Warning&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Now, Let&amp;#39;s Access the Dark Web&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Brave Browser&lt;/strong&gt;: Launch the Brave browser on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open a New Private Window with Tor&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Customize and control Brave&lt;/strong&gt; icon (the three-line menu in the top right corner). From the dropdown, select &lt;strong&gt;New private window with Tor&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;   &amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/public/main/img1.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Image of Brave browser&amp;quot; style={{ display: &amp;#39;block&amp;#39;, margin: &amp;#39;0 auto&amp;#39; }} /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connection to Tor Network&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;Once you open the new window, the browser will begin establishing a connection with the Tor network. The window will indicate that it is in &lt;strong&gt;private mode&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;   &amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/public/main/img2.png&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Image of Brave browser&amp;quot; style={{ display: &amp;#39;block&amp;#39;, margin: &amp;#39;0 auto&amp;#39; }} /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-establishing Connection (If Needed)&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;If the connection takes longer than expected, simply click to &lt;strong&gt;re-establish the connection&lt;/strong&gt; to the Tor network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the GitHub repository from the provided links sample above, simply copy any of the links and paste it into the search bar. You can also use &lt;a href=&quot;http://freshcprpapf5tduki7olsr7k4dgrjzvqnzx323qkdlqn6yoy74qp6id.onion/&quot;&gt;Fresh Onion&lt;/a&gt; to find additional onion links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&amp;quot;/public/main/fresh-onion.webp&amp;quot; alt=&amp;quot;Image of Brave browser&amp;quot; style={{ display: &amp;#39;block&amp;#39;, margin: &amp;#39;0 auto&amp;#39; }} /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Info&gt;
I hope you enjoyed this guide on how to securely access the dark web. Remember, it’s important to dive deeper into understanding how to browse safely and protect yourself while exploring this space.
&lt;/Info&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Malicious Document Analysis Walkthrough</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/analyse-malicious-doc/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/analyse-malicious-doc/</guid><description>This walkthrough guides you through the analysis of malicious documents using various tools and techniques.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/analyse-malicious-doc/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/analyse-malicious-doc/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Course Files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://app.letsdefend.io/training/lesson_detail/analysis-with-sandboxes&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source --&amp;gt; letsdefend.io&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the course files for the analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://letsdefend-images.s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/Courses/MaliciousDocumentAnalysis-Malware-Samples/PO-465514-180820.doc.zip&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PO-465514-180820.doc.zip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://letsdefend-images.s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/Courses/MaliciousDocumentAnalysis-Malware-Samples/Siparis_17.xls.zip&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Siparis_17.xls.zip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://letsdefend-images.s3.us-east-2.amazonaws.com/Courses/MaliciousDocumentAnalysis-Malware-Samples/baddoc.zip&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;baddoc.zip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Password&lt;/strong&gt;: infected&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;Warning&gt;⚠️ &lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; Do not analyze malicious files on your personal or primary machine! Always use a secure, isolated environment like a virtual machine (VM) or a dedicated analysis system to avoid compromising your data and device. Malicious documents can contain dangerous payloads that may harm your system. Stay safe!&lt;/Warning&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the files and unzip them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Linux Command to Extract Files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install p7zip (if it&amp;#39;s not already installed):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo apt-get install p7zip-full
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;7z x PO-465514-180820.doc.zip
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Question 1.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt; What is the MD5 value of the &amp;quot;/root/Desktop/QuestionFiles/PO-465514-180820.doc&amp;quot; file?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Kali Linux, the MD5 value can be obtained by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;md5sum PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;d7e6921bfd008f707ba52dee374ff3db&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 2.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the file type of /home/analyst/PO-465514-180820.doc?
By looking at the file extension, we know it&amp;#39;s a .doc file. You can also verify the file type by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;file PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;doc&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Question 3.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the file /root/Desktop/QuestionFiles/PO-465514-180820.doc contain a VBA macro?
To check for VBA macros, install oletools and run olevba:
&lt;Info&gt; OLE VBA (olevba) is a tool for analyzing Microsoft Office documents, specifically for extracting and analyzing embedded VBA macros. It helps identify potentially malicious code by performing static analysis and detecting suspicious patterns. Commonly used in malware analysis and digital forensics, it supports various Office formats and outputs results in a human-readable format, making it essential for cybersecurity professionals &lt;/Info&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;sudo -H pip install -U oletools
olevba PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the file contains a macro, you will see macro code details. If not, you&amp;#39;ll get a message like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(empty macro)
No suspicious keywords or IOC found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Yes, the file contains a VBA macro&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Question 4.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the macro keyword that triggers the malicious activity in /root/Desktop/QuestionFiles/PO-465514-180820.doc?
Run the following to analyze the macros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;olevba PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/main/microKey.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;File Contains Micro&quot;&gt;
The macro keyword responsible for the malicious activity is often Document_Open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Document_Open&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 5.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who is the author of the file /root/Desktop/QuestionFiles/PO-465514-180820.doc?
To find the document’s metadata, including the author, use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;file PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;sample output&quot;&gt;
 PO-465514-180820.doc: Composite Document File V2 Document, Little Endian, Os: Windows, Version 6.2, Code page: 1252, Title: Ipsum., Author: Alexandre Riviere, Template: Normal.dotm, Revision Number: 1, Name of Creating Application: Microsoft Office Word, Create Time/Date: Tue Aug 18 09:19:00 2020, Last Saved Time/Date: Tue Aug 18 09:19:00 2020, Number of Pages: 1, Number of Words: 4, Number of Characters: 24, Security: 0
&lt;/Collapse&gt;
The output should include details like the title, author, and other metadata. In this case, the author is Alexandre Riviere.

&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;Alexandre Riviere&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 6.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the last saved time of the file /root/Desktop/QuestionFiles/PO-465514-180820.doc?
To get detailed metadata, including the last saved time, use ExifTool:
&lt;Info&gt;ExifTool is a versatile command-line application for reading, writing, and editing metadata in various file formats, particularly images. It supports numerous metadata standards like EXIF, IPTC, and XMP. Key features include batch processing, detailed metadata output, and wide format support. It&amp;#39;s widely used by photographers and digital forensics experts for comprehensive metadata management.&lt;/Info&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;exiftool PO-465514-180820.doc
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/main/lastmodified_date.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;ExifTool&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;2020-08-18 08:19:00&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 7.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From which domain is the file Siparis_17.xls trying to download content?
To analyze the macros in the Excel file, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;olevba Siparis_17.xls
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/main/domains.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;ExifTool&quot;&gt;
The domain from which the file attempts to download content should be revealed in the output.
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;hocoso.mobi&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Question 8.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many IOCs are in the file Siparis_17.xls according to the Olevba tool?
In the Olevba analysis, look for the section labeled Indicators of Compromise (IOCs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;2&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 9.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the domain ending with .kz that the file PO-465514-180820.doc is trying to access?
To determine which domain the file is trying to access, upload it to Hybrid-Analysis. After generating a report, navigate to the Relations section to view the DNS requests made.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/main/hybrid.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;ExifTool&quot;&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;www[.]msbc.kz&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Question 10.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which Windows tool is used to make connection requests in the file PO-465514-180820.doc?
Using Hybrid-Analysis, you can observe which system tools are involved in making external connection requests. In this case, the tool used is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;powershell.exe&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 11.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many DNS addresses does the file PO-465514-180820.doc contact?
Check the Hybrid-Analysis report for DNS requests made by the file. In this case, it made requests to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;5 addresses&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Question 12.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What name does the Siparis_17.xls malware document use when saving the downloaded file to the device?
Run olevba on the Excel file again and look for the specific name the malware uses when saving the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;olevba Siparis_17.xls
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
&lt;Success&gt;6LeGwKmrm.jar&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;Info&gt;Final Thoughts: This walkthrough demonstrated how to analyze potentially malicious Microsoft Office documents using tools like olevba and ExifTool. These tools help uncover the hidden macros and metadata, revealing the malicious intent of the files..&lt;/Info&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Firewall Fundamentals</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/firewallfundemental/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/firewallfundemental/</guid><description>Explore and master the Linux iptables firewall and its utilities for managing network traffic and enhancing security on Linux systems.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/firewallfundemental/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/firewallfundemental/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This room provides an introduction to the Burp Suite web application security testing framework, focusing on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A thorough introduction to Burp Suite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An overview of the various tools within the framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guidance on installing Burp Suite on your system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigation and configuration of Burp Suite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will introduce the core of Burp Suite, the Burp Proxy. This room serves as a foundational resource for understanding Burp Suite, with a greater emphasis on theory. Future rooms will adopt a more practical approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to Burp Suite, we recommend carefully reading the provided information and engaging with the tool. Hands-on experimentation is essential for grasping the fundamentals, which will significantly aid you in subsequent rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burp Suite is a Java-based framework designed for comprehensive web application penetration testing. It has become the industry standard for assessing the security of web and mobile applications, including those utilizing APIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, Burp Suite captures and manipulates HTTP/HTTPS traffic between a browser and a web server. This capability allows users to intercept requests, view, and modify them before they reach the target server or manipulate responses before they are received by the browser, making it an invaluable tool for manual web application testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Editions of Burp Suite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burp Suite is available in several editions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Edition&lt;/strong&gt;: Free for non-commercial use, it provides essential features for manual testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional Edition&lt;/strong&gt;: This unrestricted version includes advanced features such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An automated vulnerability scanner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fuzzer/brute-forcer without rate limits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project saving and report generation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A built-in API for integration with other tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access to the Burp Suite Collaborator for unique request handling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enterprise Edition&lt;/strong&gt;: Focused on continuous scanning, this edition automatically scans web applications for vulnerabilities, residing on a server for ongoing assessments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this course, we will primarily focus on the &lt;strong&gt;Burp Suite Community Edition&lt;/strong&gt;, as it provides the core functionalities needed for effective web application testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The demonstrations will utilize Burp Suite for Windows, but the functionality is consistent across versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Features of Burp Community&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Burp Suite Community offers a more limited feature set compared to the Professional edition, it still provides an impressive array of tools that are highly valuable for web application testing. Let&amp;#39;s explore some of the key features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proxy:&lt;/strong&gt; The Burp Proxy is the most renowned aspect of Burp Suite. It enables interception and modification of requests and responses while interacting with web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeater:&lt;/strong&gt; Another well-known feature. Repeater allows for capturing, modifying, and resending the same request multiple times. This functionality is particularly useful when crafting payloads through trial and error (e.g., in SQLi - Structured Query Language Injection) or testing the functionality of an endpoint for vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intruder:&lt;/strong&gt; Despite rate limitations in Burp Suite Community, Intruder allows for spraying endpoints with requests. It is commonly utilized for brute-force attacks or fuzzing endpoints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoder:&lt;/strong&gt; Decoder offers a valuable service for data transformation. It can decode captured information or encode payloads before sending them to the target. While alternative services exist for this purpose, leveraging Decoder within Burp Suite can be highly efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparer:&lt;/strong&gt; As the name suggests, Comparer enables the comparison of two pieces of data at either the word or byte level. While not exclusive to Burp Suite, the ability to send potentially large data segments directly to a comparison tool with a single keyboard shortcut significantly accelerates the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sequencer:&lt;/strong&gt; Sequencer is typically employed when assessing the randomness of tokens, such as session cookie values or other supposedly randomly generated data. If the algorithm used for generating these values lacks secure randomness, it can expose avenues for devastating attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the built-in features, the Java codebase of Burp Suite facilitates the development of extensions to enhance the framework&amp;#39;s functionality. These extensions can be written in Java, Python (using the Java Jython interpreter), or Ruby (using the Java JRuby interpreter). The Burp Suite Extender module allows for quick and easy loading of extensions into the framework, while the marketplace, known as the BApp Store, enables downloading of third-party modules. While certain extensions may require a professional license for integration, there are still a considerable number of extensions available for Burp Community. For instance, the Logger++ module can extend the built-in logging functionality of Burp Suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Burp Suite Features Q&amp;amp;A&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Which Burp Suite feature allows us to intercept requests between ourselves and the target?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; Proxy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Which Burp tool would we use to brute-force a login form?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; Intruder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installation Guide for Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burp Suite is a valuable tool for web and mobile application assessments, pentesting, bug bounty hunting, and debugging features in web app development. Here&amp;#39;s a guide on installing Burp Suite on different platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you use the AttackBox, Burp Suite is already installed, so you can skip this step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Downloads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download the latest version of Burp Suite for other systems, click the button below to go to their download page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kali Linux:&lt;/strong&gt; Burp Suite comes pre-installed with Kali Linux. If it&amp;#39;s missing, you can install it from the Kali apt repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux, macOS, and Windows:&lt;/strong&gt; For other operating systems, PortSwigger provides dedicated installers for Burp Suite Community and Burp Suite Professional on the Burp Suite downloads page. Choose your operating system from the dropdown menu and select Burp Suite Community Edition. Then, click the Download button to initiate the download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Run the Installer:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;Windows&lt;/strong&gt;, run the executable file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On &lt;strong&gt;Linux&lt;/strong&gt;, execute the script from the terminal (with or without &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Installation Without Sudo on Linux:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you choose not to use &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt;, Burp Suite will be installed in your home directory at &lt;code&gt;~/BurpSuiteCommunity/BurpSuiteCommunity&lt;/code&gt; and will not be added to your &lt;code&gt;PATH&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow the Installation Wizard:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The installation wizard provides clear instructions. It&amp;#39;s generally safe to accept the default settings, but it&amp;#39;s always recommended to review the installer carefully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Burp Suite is successfully installed, you can launch the application. In the next task, we will explore the initial setup and configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Dashboard of Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may use the pre-installed Burp Suite Community Edition in our AttackBox. To launch the AttackBox, click the &lt;strong&gt;Start AttackBox&lt;/strong&gt; button at the top of this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Launching Burp Suite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once you launch Burp Suite and accept the terms and conditions, you will be prompted to select a project type. In Burp Suite Community, the options are limited, and you can simply click &lt;strong&gt;Next&lt;/strong&gt; to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The next window allows you to choose the configuration for Burp Suite. It is generally recommended to keep the default settings, which are suitable for most situations. Click &lt;strong&gt;Start Burp&lt;/strong&gt; to open the main Burp Suite interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Upon opening Burp Suite for the first time, you might encounter a screen with training options. It is highly recommended to go through these training materials when you have the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;#39;t see the training screen (or in subsequent sessions), you will be presented with the Burp Dashboard, which may seem overwhelming at first. However, it will soon become familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of the Burp Dashboard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Burp Dashboard is divided into four quadrants, as labeled in counter-clockwise order starting from the top left:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tasks:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Tasks menu allows you to define background tasks that Burp Suite will perform while you use the application. In Burp Suite Community, the default “Live Passive Crawl” task, which automatically logs the pages visited, is sufficient for our purposes in this module. Burp Suite Professional offers additional features like on-demand scans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event Log:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Event log provides information about the actions performed by Burp Suite, such as starting the proxy, as well as details about connections made through Burp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Issue Activity:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This section is specific to Burp Suite Professional. It displays the vulnerabilities identified by the automated scanner, ranked by severity and filterable based on the certainty of the vulnerability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advisory:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Advisory section provides more detailed information about the identified vulnerabilities, including references and suggested remediations. This information can be exported into a report. In Burp Suite Community, this section may not show any vulnerabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the various tabs and windows of Burp Suite, you will notice question mark icons (❓).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking on these icons opens a new window with helpful information specific to that section. These help icons are invaluable when you need assistance or clarification on a particular feature, so make sure to utilize them effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By exploring the different tabs and functionalities of Burp Suite, you will gradually become familiar with its capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions and Answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What menu provides information about the actions performed by Burp Suite, such as starting the proxy, and details about connections made through Burp?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Event Log&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Navigation in Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Burp Suite, the default navigation is primarily done through the top menu bars, which allow you to switch between modules and access various sub-tabs within each module. The sub-tabs appear in a second menu bar directly below the main menu bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How Navigation Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Module Selection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top row of the menu bar displays the available modules in Burp Suite. You can click on each module to switch between them. For example, the Burp Proxy module is selected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sub-Tabs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a selected module has multiple sub-tabs, they can be accessed through the second menu bar that appears directly below the main menu bar. These sub-tabs often contain module-specific settings and options. For example, in the previous image, the Proxy Intercept sub-tab is selected within the Burp Proxy module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Detaching Tabs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you prefer to view multiple tabs separately, you can detach them into separate windows. To do this, go to the &lt;strong&gt;Window&lt;/strong&gt; option in the application menu above the Module Selection bar. From there, choose the &amp;quot;Detach&amp;quot; option, and the selected tab will open in a separate window. The detached tabs can be reattached using the same method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Keyboard Shortcuts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burp Suite also provides keyboard shortcuts for quick navigation to key tabs. By default, the following shortcuts are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Shortcut&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tab&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ctrl + Shift + D&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dashboard&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ctrl + Shift + T&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Target tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ctrl + Shift + P&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Proxy tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ctrl + Shift + I&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Intruder tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ctrl + Shift + R&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Repeater tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions and Answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Which tab does Ctrl + Shift + P switch us to?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proxy tab&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Options in Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the Burp Proxy, let&amp;#39;s explore the available options for configuring Burp Suite. There are two types of settings: Global settings (also known as User settings) and Project settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Types of Settings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Global Settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These settings affect the entire Burp Suite installation and are applied every time you start the application. They provide a baseline configuration for your Burp Suite environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Project Settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These settings are specific to the current project and apply only during the session. However, please note that Burp Suite Community Edition does not support saving projects, so any project-specific options will be lost when you close Burp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the settings, click on the &lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt; button in the top navigation bar. This will open a separate settings window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Settings Window Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Settings window, you will find a menu on the left-hand side. This menu allows you to switch between different types of settings, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Search:&lt;/strong&gt; Enables searching for specific settings using keywords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type filter:&lt;/strong&gt; Filters the settings for User and Project options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User settings:&lt;/strong&gt; Shows settings that affect the entire Burp Suite installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project settings:&lt;/strong&gt; Displays settings specific to the current project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Categories:&lt;/strong&gt; Allows selecting settings by category.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s worth noting that many tools within Burp Suite provide shortcuts to specific categories of settings. For example, the Proxy module includes a Proxy settings button that opens the settings window directly to the relevant proxy section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The search feature on the settings page is a valuable addition, allowing you to quickly search for settings using keywords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take some time to familiarize yourself with the range of configurable options in Burp Suite. Once you are comfortable, you can proceed with the exercises related to configuring Burp Suite settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions and Answers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In which category can you find a reference to a &amp;quot;Cookie jar&amp;quot;?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Session Handling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;In which base category can you find the &amp;quot;Updates&amp;quot; sub-category, which controls the Burp Suite update behaviour?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User settings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is the name of the sub-category which allows you to change the keybindings for shortcuts in Burp Suite?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key Bindings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;If we have uploaded Client-Side TLS certificates, can we override these on a per-project basis (yea/nay)?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction to the Burp Proxy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Burp Proxy is a fundamental tool within Burp Suite that captures requests and responses between the user and the target web server. This intercepted traffic can be manipulated, processed with other tools, or allowed to continue to its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key Points to Understand About the Burp Proxy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intercepting Requests:&lt;/strong&gt; Requests made through the Burp Proxy are intercepted and held back from reaching the target server. They can be viewed in the Proxy tab for actions like forwarding, dropping, editing, or sending to other Burp modules. To disable interception, click the &amp;quot;Intercept is on&amp;quot; button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taking Control:&lt;/strong&gt; The ability to intercept requests empowers testers to gain complete control over web traffic, making it invaluable for testing web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Capture and Logging:&lt;/strong&gt; Burp Suite captures and logs requests by default, even when interception is off, allowing for later analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WebSocket Support:&lt;/strong&gt; Burp Suite captures and logs WebSocket communication, aiding in the analysis of web applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logs and History:&lt;/strong&gt; Captured requests can be viewed in the HTTP history and WebSockets history sub-tabs, facilitating retrospective analysis and forwarding to other Burp modules as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Proxy Settings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access proxy-specific options via the Proxy settings button to optimize usage. Notable features include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Response Interception:&lt;/strong&gt; By default, server responses are not intercepted unless specified. The &amp;quot;Intercept responses based on the following rules&amp;quot; checkbox allows for flexible response interception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Match and Replace:&lt;/strong&gt; This feature uses regular expressions (regex) to modify incoming and outgoing requests, enabling dynamic changes like modifying the user agent or manipulating cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take time to explore and experiment with these options to enhance your understanding and proficiency with the Burp Proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Connecting through the Proxy (FoxyProxy)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start the machine by clicking the &lt;strong&gt;Start Machine&lt;/strong&gt; button below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Start Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use the Burp Suite Proxy, we need to configure our local web browser to redirect traffic through Burp Suite. In this task, we will focus on configuring the proxy using the FoxyProxy extension in Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The instructions provided are specific to Firefox. If you are using a different browser, you may need to find alternative methods or use the TryHackMe AttackBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Steps to Configure Burp Suite Proxy with FoxyProxy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Install FoxyProxy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download and install the FoxyProxy Basic extension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; FoxyProxy is already installed on the AttackBox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Access FoxyProxy Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once installed, a button will appear at the top right of the Firefox browser. Click on the FoxyProxy button to access the FoxyProxy options pop-up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Create Burp Proxy Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the FoxyProxy options pop-up, click the &lt;strong&gt;Options&lt;/strong&gt; button. This will open a new browser tab with the FoxyProxy configurations. Click the &lt;strong&gt;Add&lt;/strong&gt; button to create a new proxy configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4. Add Proxy Details&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &amp;quot;Add Proxy&amp;quot; page, fill in the following values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Burp (or any preferred name)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proxy IP:&lt;/strong&gt; 127.0.0.1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port:&lt;/strong&gt; 8080&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;5. Save Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Save&lt;/strong&gt; to save the Burp Proxy configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Activate Proxy Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the FoxyProxy icon at the top-right of the Firefox browser and select the Burp configuration. This will redirect your browser traffic through 127.0.0.1:8080. &lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Burp Suite must be running for your browser to make requests when this configuration is activated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Enable Proxy Intercept in Burp Suite&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Switch to Burp Suite and ensure that &lt;strong&gt;Intercept&lt;/strong&gt; is turned on in the Proxy tab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. Test the Proxy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open Firefox and try accessing a website, such as the homepage for &lt;code&gt;http://MACHINE_IP/&lt;/code&gt;. Your browser will hang, and the proxy will populate with the HTTP request. Congratulations, you have successfully intercepted your first request!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Important Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the proxy configuration is active, and the intercept is switched on in Burp Suite, your browser will hang whenever you make a request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be cautious not to leave the intercept switched on unintentionally, as it can prevent your browser from making any requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-clicking on a request in Burp Suite allows you to perform various actions, such as forwarding, dropping, sending to other tools, or selecting options from the right-click menu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider closing the other tabs in the AttackBox browser before enabling interception, as you will receive some WebSocket requests instead of requests from the target VM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take note of these details as you begin using the Burp Suite Proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Site Map and Issue Definitions in Burp Suite&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Target tab in Burp Suite is essential for controlling the scope of testing and includes three key sub-tabs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Site Map&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functionality&lt;/strong&gt;: Displays a tree structure of the web applications being tested.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage&lt;/strong&gt;: Automatically generates a site map by browsing the application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional Features&lt;/strong&gt;: Allows for automated crawling to explore links between pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Features&lt;/strong&gt;: Useful for initial enumeration, especially for mapping APIs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Issue Definitions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt;: Contains a list of vulnerabilities that Burp Suite&amp;#39;s scanner checks for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utility&lt;/strong&gt;: Valuable for referencing vulnerabilities in reports and assisting in manual testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Scope Settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;: Defines the target scope by including or excluding specific domains/IPs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefit&lt;/strong&gt;: Helps focus testing on specific applications and avoid irrelevant traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Challenge: Mapping and Identifying Unusual Endpoints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visit the site at &lt;code&gt;http://MACHINE_IP/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore every page linked from the homepage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the sitemap for an unusual endpoint that stands out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze the endpoint in your browser or via the &amp;quot;Response&amp;quot; section of the site map entry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Endpoint Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unusual Endpoint&lt;/strong&gt;: [Endpoint URL]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;: [Brief description of what makes it unusual]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: [Summary of findings from the endpoint response]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Replace placeholders with actual data after exploring the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Burp Suite Browser&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burp Suite includes a built-in Chromium browser that is pre-configured to use the proxy, simplifying the setup compared to modifying a regular web browser. To open the Burp Browser, click the &lt;strong&gt;Open Browser&lt;/strong&gt; button in the proxy tab, and a Chromium window will appear, routing all requests through the proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Explore the various settings related to the Burp Browser in the project and user options to customize it as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Running Burp Suite on Linux as Root&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are running Burp Suite on Linux as the root user (like in the AttackBox), you may face issues starting the Burp Browser due to sandbox restrictions. Here are two solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smart Option&lt;/strong&gt;: Create a new user and run Burp Suite under a low-privilege account to avoid issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easy Option&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to &lt;strong&gt;Settings&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Tools&lt;/strong&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;strong&gt;Burp&amp;#39;s browser&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the &lt;strong&gt;Allow Burp&amp;#39;s browser to run without a sandbox&lt;/strong&gt; option.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will enable the browser to start without a sandbox but is disabled by default for security reasons. If enabled, exercise caution, as this could expose your machine to risks. In a training environment like the AttackBox, the risk is minimal, but be mindful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Scoping and Targeting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scoping is a crucial aspect of using the Burp Proxy, allowing you to focus on specific web applications instead of capturing all traffic, which can be overwhelming. By defining a scope for the project, you can control what gets proxied and logged in Burp Suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting the Scope&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add to Scope&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Switch to the &lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click on your target from the list on the left.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select &lt;strong&gt;Add To Scope&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burp will prompt you to stop logging anything not in scope; usually, you should select &amp;quot;yes.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check Your Scope&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the &lt;strong&gt;Scope settings&lt;/strong&gt; sub-tab within the Target tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This window allows you to include or exclude specific domains/IPs, making it essential to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prevent Interception of Out-of-Scope Traffic&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even if logging is disabled for out-of-scope traffic, the proxy will still intercept everything.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To prevent this, go to the &lt;strong&gt;Proxy settings&lt;/strong&gt; sub-tab and select &lt;strong&gt;And URL Is in target scope&lt;/strong&gt; under the &amp;quot;Intercept Client Requests&amp;quot; section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling this option ensures that the proxy ignores any traffic not within the defined scope, resulting in a cleaner view of traffic in Burp Suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is scoping important in Burp Suite?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scoping is important because it allows testers to focus on specific web applications, reducing clutter and enhancing the efficiency of testing efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can you add a target to the scope?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can add a target by right-clicking on it in the Target tab and selecting &lt;strong&gt;Add To Scope&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happens if you disable logging for out-of-scope traffic?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If logging is disabled, the proxy will still intercept all traffic unless you also configure the proxy settings to ignore out-of-scope requests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where can you manage the target scope?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can manage the target scope in the &lt;strong&gt;Scope settings&lt;/strong&gt; sub-tab within the Target tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What option should you enable to avoid clutter from out-of-scope traffic?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You should enable the &lt;strong&gt;And URL Is in target scope&lt;/strong&gt; option in the Proxy settings to ignore out-of-scope traffic completely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Proxying HTTPS&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When intercepting HTTP traffic, issues may arise when navigating to sites with TLS enabled, such as accessing &lt;code&gt;https://google.com/&lt;/code&gt;. You might receive an error indicating that the PortSwigger Certificate Authority (CA) is not authorized to secure the connection because the browser does not trust the certificate presented by Burp Suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Steps to Trust the PortSwigger CA Certificate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To resolve this issue, you can manually add the PortSwigger CA certificate to your browser&amp;#39;s trusted certificate authorities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download the CA Certificate&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the Burp Proxy activated, navigate to &lt;a href=&quot;http://burp/cert&quot;&gt;http://burp/cert&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will download a file called &lt;code&gt;cacert.der&lt;/code&gt;. Save it to your machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Firefox Certificate Settings&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Type &lt;code&gt;about:preferences&lt;/code&gt; into your Firefox URL bar and press Enter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for &amp;quot;certificates&amp;quot; and click on the &lt;strong&gt;View Certificates&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Import the CA Certificate&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the Certificate Manager window, click on the &lt;strong&gt;Import&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the &lt;code&gt;cacert.der&lt;/code&gt; file you downloaded earlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set Trust for the CA Certificate&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the next window, check the box that says &lt;strong&gt;Trust this CA to identify websites&lt;/strong&gt; and click OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By completing these steps, you will have added the PortSwigger CA certificate to your list of trusted certificate authorities, allowing you to visit any TLS-enabled site without encountering certificate errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: You can watch a video demonstration of the full certificate import process for further guidance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following these instructions, your browser will trust the PortSwigger CA certificate, enabling secure communication with TLS-enabled websites through the Burp Suite Proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XSS Attack on a Support Form&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Understanding the Attack:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example demonstrates a &amp;quot;Reflected&amp;quot; XSS attack, where malicious code is injected into a web page to be executed by the user&amp;#39;s browser. In this case, the attack targets a support form and exploits a vulnerability in the form&amp;#39;s input validation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps Involved:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify the Target:&lt;/strong&gt; The support form&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Contact Email&amp;quot; field is selected as the potential target for the XSS attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Construct the Payload:&lt;/strong&gt; A simple JavaScript payload is created: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;alert(&amp;quot;Succ3ssful XSS&amp;quot;)&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. This payload will display an alert message if executed successfully.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bypass Input Validation:&lt;/strong&gt; The attacker attempts to directly enter the payload into the form. However, the form&amp;#39;s client-side validation prevents the submission of special characters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;URL Encoding:&lt;/strong&gt; To circumvent the validation, the payload is URL-encoded using the Ctrl+U shortcut in Burp Suite. This makes the payload safe to send.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Send the Request:&lt;/strong&gt; The modified request, containing the URL-encoded payload, is sent to the server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Execute the Payload:&lt;/strong&gt; The server processes the request and returns the modified page to the user&amp;#39;s browser. The browser interprets the URL-encoded payload as JavaScript and executes it, resulting in the alert message being displayed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example highlights the importance of proper input validation to prevent XSS attacks. By understanding how XSS works and implementing appropriate security measures, developers can protect their web applications from such vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While this example demonstrates a basic XSS attack, real-world attacks can be much more complex and damaging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s essential to use a web application firewall (WAF) and other security measures to mitigate the risk of XSS and other web-based attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always keep your web application and its components up-to-date with the latest security patches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on completing the Burp Basics room! You now have a solid understanding of the Burp Suite interface and its key features. These skills are essential for your journey in web and mobile application penetration testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve your skills, practice using Burp Suite, explore its features, and familiarize yourself with its tools. The more you engage with it, the better you&amp;#39;ll become at identifying and exploiting vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next module, we will focus on Burp Suite Repeater, a powerful tool for manual testing and request manipulation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay curious and keep learning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/burpsuitebasics&quot;&gt;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/burpsuitebasics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Legal Considerations in DFIR</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/legalconsideration-dfr/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/legalconsideration-dfr/</guid><description>Understand the processes involved in DFIR and the legal considerations that guide them.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/legalconsideration-dfr/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/legalconsideration-dfr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction to Digital Forensics and Incident Response (DFIR)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital Forensics and Incident Response (DFIR) encompasses the systematic process of detecting, investigating, and responding to cybersecurity incidents while ensuring legal integrity. The principles underlying DFIR are vital for effective incident management, legal compliance, and maintaining the trustworthiness of digital evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Principles of DFIR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preservation of Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure that digital evidence is maintained in its original state to prevent tampering or alteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identification and Collection&lt;/strong&gt;: Quickly identify and collect relevant data from compromised systems while adhering to legal standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: Conduct a thorough examination of the data to understand the scope and impact of the incident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reporting and Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;: Document all findings and actions taken during the investigation for accountability and future reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ethical Considerations in Digital Investigations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical practices are crucial in DFIR to protect the rights of individuals and organizations involved. Investigators must ensure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality&lt;/strong&gt;: Safeguarding sensitive information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrity&lt;/strong&gt;: Conducting investigations without bias or conflict of interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;: Providing clear and accurate reporting of findings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Importance of Chain of Custody&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chain of Custody refers to the documented process that tracks the handling of evidence from the moment it is collected until it is presented in court. Its importance includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legal Admissibility&lt;/strong&gt;: Maintaining a clear chain helps establish the authenticity of evidence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensures that all individuals involved in the handling of evidence are documented and responsible for their actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Legal Standards for Acquiring Forensic Disk Images&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adhering to legal standards during the acquisition of forensic images is essential to ensure their admissibility in court:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authorization&lt;/strong&gt;: Obtain necessary permissions before accessing systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use of Forensic Tools&lt;/strong&gt;: Utilize verified and industry-standard tools for imaging to avoid data alteration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;: Record the process meticulously, including date, time, and methods used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Best Practices for Analyzing Digital Evidence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure compliance with legal and regulatory standards during analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Write Blockers&lt;/strong&gt;: Prevent alteration of data when accessing storage media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maintain Original Evidence&lt;/strong&gt;: Always work from copies of the data, keeping the original evidence untouched.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Established Protocols&lt;/strong&gt;: Adhere to frameworks like the NIST guidelines for digital forensics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage Legal Counsel&lt;/strong&gt;: Involve legal advisors during investigations to ensure compliance with laws and regulations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Room Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incident Response Module&lt;/strong&gt;: Understanding initial response strategies to security breaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Becoming a First Responder&lt;/strong&gt;: Training to recognize and assess security incidents swiftly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Connecting to the Virtual Machine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin the practical aspect of this module:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click the green &amp;quot;Start Machine&amp;quot; button in the upper right section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the VM is not visible, select the &amp;quot;Show Split View&amp;quot; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect via RDP using provided credentials if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait approximately 4 minutes for the VM to fully deploy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Microsoft Outlook will launch automatically; follow the instructions to bypass activation prompts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Incident Detection and Initial Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Incident Scenario&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chief Finance Officer (CFO) received an email receipt for an unauthorized transaction over $9,000. Both the CFO and their Executive Assistant (EA) deny making the purchase. The CFO alerted the Human Resources (HR) and Security Operations (SecOps) team to investigate the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Importance of Incident Detection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incident detection relies not only on technical controls but also on the involvement of individuals. Responders must remain calm, understand the situation, and gather information from various sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Initial Response&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial response is influenced by the incident&amp;#39;s nature and the responder&amp;#39;s experience. It typically involves piecing together evidence and using investigative techniques and tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Importance of Documentation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thorough documentation is crucial. Key points to document include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Details on persons of interest and their involvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actions leading to the incident, such as interacting with a phishing site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nature and extent of compromised data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any evidence that sheds light on the incident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if browsing history is missing, other sources like network logs can reveal traces of the incident. It’s essential to note important timestamps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The date and time the incident was detected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The timeline of events leading to detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Response actions taken after detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding the Cause&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding why the incident happened helps strengthen security. Important aspects include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyzing how the phishing scam was successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identifying knowledge or communication gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formulating recommendations for policy and training updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Documentation and Court Admissibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proper documentation ensures that evidence can be presented in court. Clear records strengthen the legal standing of the actions taken.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations/incident-note.png&quot; alt=&quot;incident note&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Standard Operating Procedures for Communication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Establishing communication protocols is vital during an incident. Key points include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utilization of Designated Channels&lt;/strong&gt;: Use structured approaches for reporting and urgent communications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timely Notification&lt;/strong&gt;: Inform key stakeholders promptly to initiate coordinated responses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarity and Consistency&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure messages are clear and prevent misinformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Compliance&lt;/strong&gt;: Meet legal requirements to mitigate potential repercussions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Incident Response Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A robust Incident Response (IR) process is essential for effective communication and management:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear Reporting Path&lt;/strong&gt;: Inform constituents about the process for reporting concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defined Roles and Responsibilities&lt;/strong&gt;: Ensure each team member knows their tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continual Updates&lt;/strong&gt;: Regularly update all parties as the situation evolves.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post-Incident Review&lt;/strong&gt;: Effective communication aids in identifying lessons learned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reminder&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you proceed with the tasks, think like an incident responder. Focus on advancing the investigation by following procedures and utilizing your skills. Your decisions should align with the scenario&amp;#39;s objectives. Now, let&amp;#39;s proceed with the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the Ticket# of the reported incident?
in the list of mails look for &lt;code&gt;NoReply: SupportMe Workflow&lt;/code&gt; click on the mail, in the table look for &lt;code&gt;OTRS ticket Number&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations/report-ticket.png&quot; alt=&quot;incident note&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;2024011900041521&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the email of the primary person of interest (POI)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;Success&gt;A Person of Interest (POI) in incident response is someone relevant to the investigation of a security incident. They may be directly involved, a witness, or have useful information. Identifying and documenting POIs is crucial, as their insights can help clarify the incident and support prevention strategies and legal actions&lt;/Success&gt;
 to answer this question, i look through the recived  mails, and i found one mail give a summary of Participants the role and responsibilities
 it looks something like this &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-mdx&quot;&gt;Meeting Summary

Participants
- @John
- @Oliver
- @Emily
- @Zoe
- @Michael
- @Alice

Thank you all for attending this meeting on such short notice. Your prompt response and commitment are greatly appreciated under these circumstances.

Key Action Points
- Michael will initiate the process by formally opening a SupportMe Ticket to document and track the issue.
- Oliver is appointed the lead investigator into the unauthorized transaction, with John providing crucial support.
- Alice shared her Outlook OST file with Oliver during the call as requested for a detailed examination of her email activities and potential phishing attempts.
- John will collaborate with Derick&amp;#39;s team to secure and analyze relevant logs to identify any signs of a security breach.
- Alice and Michael will jointly review the invoicing platform, scrutinizing it for other suspicious financial activities.
- Emily will oversee the overall investigation and provide regular updates to senior management, ensuring transparency and timely resolution.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so we can clearly see the POI is &lt;code&gt;Alice&lt;/code&gt;, and i scrolled down and obtained the mail
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aliceranallo@swiftspend.finance&quot;&gt;aliceranallo@swiftspend.finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is the POI reporting to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Michael ascot&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What specific kind of logs was requested from IT?
as we cann see in the image below john is requesting for Exchange IIS server logs 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations/logs.png&quot; alt=&quot;logs type&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Exchange Server IIS logs&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the timestamp of IT&amp;#39;s response to the request for logs?
if look at the top of the mail, we can see the timestamp
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations/time.png&quot; alt=&quot;timestamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Fri 1/19/2024 7:34 PM&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ethical Decision-Making and Legal Compliance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Evidence-based Approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital forensics practitioners must avoid making hasty conclusions. Viewing a person of interest through a biased lens can compromise the integrity of an investigation. An evidence-based approach ensures thorough investigations that adhere to legal standards, focusing on what the evidence shows and allowing for repeatable, credible conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Burden of Proof in Digital Forensics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investigators must provide sufficient, credible evidence to support their findings. The burden of proof ensures that conclusions are legally defensible, requiring adherence to high standards of evidence and ethical guidelines throughout the investigative process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ethical Decision-Making&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethical decision-making is vital in investigations to prevent illegal or unethical actions. Practitioners must respect privacy and perform only authorized actions during investigations. Ethical issues often arise regarding the handling of personal and sensitive information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Legal Compliance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Legal compliance is fundamental in digital forensics, governed by frameworks like the Sarbanes-Oxley Act (SOX) and the Computer Fraud and Abuse Act (CFAA). These laws impact how digital investigations are conducted, emphasizing the need for an evidence-based approach that respects individual rights while uncovering the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Responsibility of Authority in Digital Investigations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authority figures, including incident responders and law enforcement, hold significant responsibility for maintaining the integrity of investigations. They must set guidelines, provide oversight, and promote a culture of ethical decision-making while staying updated on legal standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Understanding Authority&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recognizing authority in digital investigations is crucial. Legal decisions are ultimately made by judges and lawmakers, highlighting the importance of respecting their interpretations of laws like SOX and CFAA. Incident responders must balance personal ethics with professional conduct and legal compliance to ensure effective investigations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations/commuication.png&quot; alt=&quot;timestamp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the above pictures to answers the below questions &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on email communications, what clause of the Acceptable Use Policy (AUP) email received by the POI did they violate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;personal use of coporate email&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;


&lt;p&gt;-Based on email communications, what anomaly did your colleague suggest looking for within the Front-end and Back-end IIS logs of the Server?
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;Unauthorised Remote Logins&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the User-Agent of the anomalous IP address with a successful login attempt?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Networking Concepts</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/networking-concept/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/networking-concept/</guid><description>Learn about the ISO OSI model and the TCP/IP protocol suite.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/networking-concept/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/networking-concept/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Networking Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some valuable resources to learn about networking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TryHackMe Modules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/networkingconcepts&quot;&gt;Networking Concepts on TryHackMe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/module/network-fundamentals&quot;&gt;Network Fundamentals Module on TryHackMe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/module/intro-to-networking&quot;&gt;Introduction to Networking Module on TryHackMe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/module/network-security&quot;&gt;Network Security Module on TryHackMe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/module/network-security-and-traffic-analysis&quot;&gt;Network Security and Traffic Analysis Module on TryHackMe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;External Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cisco.com/c/en/us/solutions/small-business/resource-center/networking-basics.html&quot;&gt;Cisco Networking Basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.comptia.org/certifications/network&quot;&gt;CompTIA Network+ Certification Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/course/networking-for-beginners/&quot;&gt;Networking for Beginners on Udemy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/course/networking-fundamentals&quot;&gt;Networking Fundamentals on edX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3QhU9y8eKUw&quot;&gt;How the Internet Works - YouTube Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why you need an IP address to access the Internet? Is it true that an IP address can uniquely identify the user? Are you curious to learn what the life of a packet looks like? If the answer is yes, let’s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This room is the first room in a series of four rooms dedicated to introducing the user to vital networking concepts and the most common networking protocols:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networking Concepts&lt;/strong&gt; (this room)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networking Essentials&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/networkingessentials&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networking Core Protocols&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/networkingcoreprotocols&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Networking Secure Protocols&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Room Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This room expects that you know terms such as IP address and TCP port number; however, we don’t expect that the reader is able to explain such terms in proper technical depth. If you are unfamiliar with these terms, please consider joining the Pre Security path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Learning Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time you finish this room, you will have learned about the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ISO OSI network model&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP addresses, subnets, and routing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TCP, UDP, and port numbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to connect to an open TCP port from the command line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OSI Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we start, we should note that the OSI model might initially seem complicated. Don’t worry if you encounter cryptic acronyms, as we provide examples of the OSI model layers. We assure you that by the time you finish this module, this task will feel like a piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The OSI (Open Systems Interconnection) model is a conceptual model developed by the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) that describes how communications should occur in a computer network. In other words, the OSI model defines a framework for computer network communications. Although this model is theoretical, it is vital to learn and understand as it helps grasp networking concepts on a deeper level. The OSI model is composed of seven layers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Link Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presentation Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbering starts with the physical layer being layer 1, while the top layer, the application layer, is layer 7. To help you remember the layers from bottom to top, you can use a mnemonic such as “Please Do Not Throw Spinach Pizza Away.” You can check the Internet for other easy-to-remember acronyms if this helps you memorize them. Remembering the OSI model layers with their layer numbers is important; otherwise, you will struggle to understand terms such as “layer 3 switch” or “layer 7 firewall.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Seven Layers of the OSI Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/layers.png&quot; alt=&quot;OSI Models&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Layer 1: Physical Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The physical layer, also referred to as layer 1, deals with the physical connection between devices; this includes the medium, such as a wire, and the definition of the binary digits 0 and 1. Data transmission can be via an electrical, optical, or wireless signal. Consequently, we need data cables or antennas, depending on our physical medium.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/layer.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Layer 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of the physical layer medium include Ethernet cable, optical fiber cable, and WiFi radio bands (2.4 GHz, 5 GHz, 6 GHz).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layer 2: Data Link Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data link layer, i.e., layer 2, represents the protocol that enables data transfer between nodes on the same network segment. This layer describes an agreement between different systems on how to communicate. For example, a company office with ten computers connected to a network switch represents a network segment.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/layer2.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Layer 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of layer 2 include Ethernet (802.3) and WiFi (802.11). Ethernet and WiFi addresses are called MAC addresses (Media Access Control), expressed in hexadecimal format. A MAC address consists of six octets, where the three leftmost bytes identify the vendor.
We expect to see two MAC addresses in each frame in real network communication over Ethernet or WiFi. The packet in the screenshot below shows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The destination data-link address (MAC address) highlighted in yellow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The source data link address (MAC address) is highlighted in blue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The remaining bits show the data being sent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/wireshark.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wireshark imag&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Layer 3: Network Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network layer, i.e., layer 3, is concerned with sending data between different networks. It handles logical addressing and routing, i.e., finding a path to transfer the network packets between diverse networks.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/topology.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Wireshark imag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of the network layer include Internet Protocol (IP), Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP), and Virtual Private Network (VPN) protocols such as IPSec and SSL/TLS VPN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layer 4: Transport Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layer 4, the transport layer, enables end-to-end communication between running applications on different hosts. It supports functions like flow control, segmentation, and error correction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of layer 4 are Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) and User Datagram Protocol (UDP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layer 5: Session Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session layer is responsible for establishing, maintaining, and synchronizing communication between applications running on different hosts. It negotiates necessary parameters for the session and ensures data synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Examples of the session layer are Network File System (NFS) and Remote Procedure Call (RPC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layer 6: Presentation Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation layer ensures data is delivered in a form the application layer can understand. It handles data encoding, compression, and encryption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standards at the presentation layer include character encoding (ASCII, Unicode) and file formats (JPEG, GIF, PNG). MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) is often used to encode binary files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Layer 7: Application Layer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application layer provides network services directly to end-user applications. Examples include protocols like HTTP, FTP, DNS, POP3, SMTP, and IMAP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading about the ISO OSI model for the first time can be intimidating; however, it becomes easier as you progress in your study of networking protocols. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OSI Model Summary Table&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Layer Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Layer Name&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Main Function&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Example Protocols and Standards&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Providing services and interfaces to applications&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HTTP, FTP, DNS, POP3, SMTP, IMAP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Presentation layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Data encoding, encryption, and compression&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unicode, MIME, JPEG, PNG, MPEG&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Session layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Establishing, maintaining, and synchronizing sessions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NFS, RPC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Transport layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;End-to-end communication and data segmentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;UDP, TCP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Network layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logical addressing and routing between networks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IP, ICMP, IPSec&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Data link layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reliable data transfer between adjacent nodes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ethernet (802.3), WiFi (802.11)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Layer 1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physical layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physical data transmission media&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Electrical, optical, and wireless signals&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TCP/IP Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have covered the conceptual ISO OSI model, it is time to study an implemented model, the TCP/IP model. TCP/IP stands for Transmission Control Protocol/Internet Protocol and was developed in the 1970s by the Department of Defense (DoD). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hear you ask why the DoD would create such a model. One of the strengths of this model is that it allows a network to continue to function as parts of it are out of service, for instance, due to a military attack. This capability is possible in part due to the design of the routing protocols to adapt as the network topology changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our presentation of the ISO OSI model, we went from bottom to top, from layer 1 to layer 7. In this task, let’s look at things from a different perspective, from top to bottom. From top to bottom, we have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Layer:&lt;/strong&gt; The OSI model application, presentation, and session layers (i.e., layers 5, 6, and 7) are grouped into the application layer in the TCP/IP model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport Layer:&lt;/strong&gt; This is layer 4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internet Layer:&lt;/strong&gt; This is layer 3. The OSI model’s network layer is called the Internet layer in the TCP/IP model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link Layer:&lt;/strong&gt; This is layer 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TCP/IP Model vs. ISO/OSI Model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table below shows how the TCP/IP model layers map to the ISO/OSI model layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Layer Number&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;ISO OSI Model&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;TCP/IP Model (RFC 1122)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Protocols&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Application Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HTTP, HTTPS, FTP, POP3, SMTP, IMAP, Telnet, SSH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Presentation Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Session Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Transport Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Transport Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;TCP, UDP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Network Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Internet Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IP, ICMP, IPSec&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Data Link Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Link Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ethernet 802.3, WiFi 802.11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Physical Layer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many modern networking textbooks show the TCP/IP model as five layers instead of four. For example, in &lt;em&gt;Computer Networking: A Top-Down Approach&lt;/em&gt; (8th Edition) by Kurose and Ross, the following five-layer Internet protocol stack is described, including the physical layer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following tasks, we will cover the IP protocol from the Internet layer and the UDP and TCP protocols from the transport layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IP Addresses and Subnets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you hear the word IP address, you might think of an address like 192.168.0.1 or something less common, such as 172.16.159.243. In both cases, you are right. Both of these are IP addresses; IPv4 (IP version 4) addresses to be specific.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every host on the network needs a unique identifier for other hosts to communicate with him. Without a unique identifier, the host cannot be found without ambiguity. When using the TCP/IP protocol suite, we need to assign an IP address for each device connected to the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One analogy of an IP address is your home postal address. Your postal address allows you to receive letters and parcels from all over the world. Furthermore, it can identify your home without ambiguity; otherwise, you cannot shop online!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might already know, we have IPv4 and IPv6 (IP version 6). IPv4 is still the most common, and whenever you come across a text mentioning IP without the version, we expect them to mean IPv4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what makes an IP address? An IP address comprises four octets, i.e., 32 bits. Being 8 bits, an octet allows us to represent a decimal number between 0 and 255. An IP address is shown in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An IP address is made up of 4 octets or bytes and each octet represents a decimal number between 0 and 255.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the risk of oversimplifying things, the 0 and 255 are reserved for the network and broadcast addresses, respectively. In other words, 192.168.1.0 is the network address, while 192.168.1.255 is the broadcast address. Sending to the broadcast address targets all the hosts on the network. With simple math, you can conclude that we cannot have more than 4 billion unique IPv4 addresses. If you are curious about the math, it is approximately 232 because we have 32 bits. This number is approximate because we didn’t consider network and broadcast addresses.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/ip.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wireshark imag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Looking Up Your Network Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can look up your IP address on the MS Windows command line using the command ipconfig. On Linux and UNIX-based systems, you can issue the command ifconfig or ip address show, which can be typed as ip a s. In the terminal window below, we show ifconfig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@TryHackMe$ ifconfig
[...]
wlo1: flags=4163&amp;lt;UP,BROADCAST,RUNNING,MULTICAST&amp;gt;  mtu 1500
        inet 192.168.66.89  netmask 255.255.255.0  broadcast 192.168.66.255
        inet6 fe80::73e1:ca5e:3f93:b1b3  prefixlen 64  scopeid 0x20&amp;lt;link&amp;gt;
        ether cc:5e:f8:02:21:a7  txqueuelen 1000  (Ethernet)
        RX packets 19684680  bytes 18865072842 (17.5 GiB)
        RX errors 0  dropped 364  overruns 0  frame 0
        TX packets 14439678  bytes 8773200951 (8.1 GiB)
        TX errors 0  dropped 0 overruns 0  carrier 0  collisions 0
The terminal output above indicates the following:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The host (laptop) IP address is 192.168.66.89&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The subnet mask is 255.255.255.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The broadcast address is 192.168.66.255
Let’s use ip a s to compare how the network card IP address is presented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@TryHackMe$ ip a s
[...]
4: wlo1: &amp;lt;BROADCAST,MULTICAST,UP,LOWER_UP&amp;gt; mtu 1500 qdisc noqueue state UP group default qlen 1000
    link/ether cc:5e:f8:02:21:a7 brd ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff
    altname wlp3s0
    inet 192.168.66.89/24 brd 192.168.66.255 scope global dynamic noprefixroute wlo1
       valid_lft 36795sec preferred_lft 36795sec
    inet6 fe80::73e1:ca5e:3f93:b1b3/64 scope link noprefixroute 
       valid_lft forever preferred_lft forever
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The terminal output above indicates the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The host (laptop) IP address is 192.168.66.89/24&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The broadcast address is 192.168.66.255
If you are wondering, a subnet mask of 255.255.255.0 can also be written as /24. The /24 means that the leftmost 24 bits within the IP address do not change across the network, i.e., the subnet. In other words, the leftmost three octets are the same across the whole subnet; therefore, we can expect to find addresses that range from 192.168.66.1 to 192.168.66.254. Similar to what was mentioned earlier, 192.168.66.0 and 192.168.66.255 are the network and broadcast addresses, respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Private Addresses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we are explaining IP addresses, it is useful to mention that for most practical purposes, there are two types of IP addresses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public IP addresses&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Private IP addresses
RFC 1918 defines the following three ranges of private IP addresses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;10.0.0.0 - 10.255.255.255 (10/8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;172.16.0.0 - 172.31.255.255 (172.16/12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;192.168.0.0 - 192.168.255.255 (192.168/16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We presented earlier an analogy stating that a public IP address is like your home postal address. A private IP address is different; the original idea is that it cannot reach or be reached from the outside world. It is like an isolated city or a compound, where all houses and apartments are numbered systematically and can easily exchange mail with each other, but not with the outside world. For a private IP address to access the Internet, the router must have a public IP address and must support Network Address Translation (NAT). At this stage, let’s not worry about understanding how NAT works, as we will revisit it later in this module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before moving on, I recommend memorising the private IP address ranges. Otherwise, you might see an IP address such as 10.1.33.7 or 172.31.33.7 and try to access it from a public IP address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Routing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A router is like your local post office; you hand them the mail parcel, and they would know how to deliver it. If we dig deeper, you might mail something to an address in another city or country. The post office will check the address and decide where to send it next. For example, if it is to leave the country, we expect one central office to handle all shipments abroad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In technical terms, a router forwards data packets to the proper network. Usually, a data packet passes through multiple routers before it reaches its final destination. The router functions at layer 3, inspecting the IP address and forwarding the packet to the best network (router) so the packet gets closer to its destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A computer network diagram showing a web server, a mobile user with a laptop, and an office user with a desktop computer. There are six routers between the three systems and there are different paths that a packet can use to travel from one system to the other.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/routing.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wireshark imag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;UDP and TCP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IP protocol allows us to reach a destination host on the network; the host is identified by its IP address. We need protocols that enable processes on networked hosts to communicate with each other. There are two transport protocols to achieve that: UDP and TCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;UDP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UDP (User Datagram Protocol) allows us to reach a specific process on the target host. UDP is a simple connectionless protocol that operates at the transport layer (i.e., layer 4). Being connectionless means that it does not need to establish a connection and does not provide a mechanism to confirm that the packet has been delivered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An IP address identifies the host, but we also need a mechanism to determine the sending and receiving process. This can be achieved using port numbers, which use two octets and range between 1 and 65535; port 0 is reserved. (The number 65535 is calculated by the expression (2^{16} - 1).)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A real-life example similar to UDP is the standard mail service, which does not provide delivery confirmation. In other words, there is no guarantee that the UDP packet has been successfully received, similar to sending a parcel via standard mail without confirmation of delivery. In standard mail, this results in a cheaper cost compared to delivery options with confirmation. In the case of UDP, it translates to better speed than a transport protocol that provides “confirmation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we want a transport protocol that acknowledges received packets? The answer lies in using TCP instead of UDP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;TCP&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TCP (Transmission Control Protocol) is a connection-oriented transport protocol. It uses various mechanisms to ensure reliable data delivery between different processes on the networked hosts. Like UDP, TCP is also a layer 4 protocol. However, being connection-oriented, it requires the establishment of a TCP connection before any data can be sent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In TCP, each data octet has a sequence number, making it easy for the receiver to identify lost or duplicated packets. The receiver acknowledges the reception of data with an acknowledgment number specifying the last received octet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A TCP connection is established using what’s called a three-way handshake. Two flags are used: SYN (Synchronize) and ACK (Acknowledgment). The packets are exchanged as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYN Packet:&lt;/strong&gt; The client initiates the connection by sending a SYN packet to the server. This packet contains the client’s randomly chosen initial sequence number.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SYN-ACK Packet:&lt;/strong&gt; The server responds to the SYN packet with a SYN-ACK packet, which includes the initial sequence number randomly chosen by the server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ACK Packet:&lt;/strong&gt; The three-way handshake is completed as the client sends an ACK packet to acknowledge the reception of the SYN-ACK packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TCP three-way handshake requires the exchange of three packets.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/handshake&quot; alt=&quot;Three way handshake imag&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to UDP, TCP identifies the process of initiating or waiting (listening) for a connection using port numbers. A valid port number ranges between 1 and 65535 because it uses two octets, and port 0 is reserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Encapsulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before wrapping up, it is crucial to explain another key concept: encapsulation. In this context, encapsulation refers to the process where each layer adds a header (and sometimes a trailer) to the received unit of data and sends the “encapsulated” unit to the layer below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encapsulation is essential as it allows each layer to focus on its intended function. Below are the four steps involved:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application Data:&lt;/strong&gt; It all starts when the user inputs the data they want to send into the application. For example, you might write an email or an instant message and hit the send button. The application formats this data and starts sending it according to the application protocol used, using the layer below it, the transport layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport Protocol Segment or Datagram:&lt;/strong&gt; The transport layer (such as TCP or UDP) adds the proper header information and creates the TCP segment (or UDP datagram). This segment is sent to the layer below it, the network layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Network Packet:&lt;/strong&gt; The network layer (i.e., the Internet layer) adds an IP header to the received TCP segment or UDP datagram. This IP packet is then sent to the layer below it, the data link layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Link Frame:&lt;/strong&gt; The Ethernet or WiFi layer receives the IP packet and adds the proper header and trailer, creating a frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application data is encapsulated within a TCP segment or UDP datagram.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The TCP segment or UDP datagram is encapsulated within an IP packet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IP packet is encapsulated within a data link frame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/encapsulation.svg&quot; alt=&quot;encapsulation imag&quot; /&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This encapsulation process must be reversed on the receiving end until the application data is extracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Life of a Packet&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on what we have studied so far, we can explain a simplified version of a packet’s life. Let’s consider the scenario where you search for a room on TryHackMe:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the TryHackMe search page, you enter your search query and hit enter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your web browser, using HTTPS, prepares an HTTP request and pushes it to the layer below it, the transport layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The TCP layer needs to establish a connection via a three-way handshake between your browser and the TryHackMe web server. After establishing the TCP connection, it can send the HTTP request containing the search query. Each TCP segment created is sent to the layer below it, the Internet layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IP layer adds the source IP address (i.e., your computer) and the destination IP address (i.e., the IP address of the TryHackMe web server). For this packet to reach the router, your laptop delivers it to the layer below it, the link layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depending on the protocol, the link layer adds the proper link layer header and trailer, and the packet is sent to the router.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The router removes the link layer header and trailer, inspects the IP destination, among other fields, and routes the packet to the proper link. Each router repeats this process until it reaches the router of the target server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The steps will then be reversed as the packet reaches the router of the destination network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we cover additional protocols, we will revisit this exercise and create a more in-depth version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Telnet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Start Machine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Start AttackBox&lt;/strong&gt; button at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;Start VM&lt;/strong&gt; button on the right to start the attached virtual machine (VM). Give both machines about 2 minutes each to properly boot up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the two machines are ready, we need to start the terminal on the AttackBox to experiment with Telnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Telnet?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TELNET (Teletype Network) protocol is a network protocol for remote terminal connection. In simpler terms, Telnet allows you to connect to and communicate with a remote system and issue text commands. Although initially used for remote administration, you can use Telnet to connect to any server listening on a TCP port number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Target Virtual Machine Services&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the target virtual machine, different services are running. We will experiment with three of them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Echo Server:&lt;/strong&gt; This server echoes everything you send it. By default, it listens on port 7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Daytime Server:&lt;/strong&gt; This server listens on port 13 by default and replies with the current day and time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web (HTTP) Server:&lt;/strong&gt; This server listens on TCP port 80 by default and serves web pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; The echo and daytime servers are considered security risks and should not be run; however, we started them explicitly to demonstrate communication with the server using Telnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Connecting with Telnet&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the terminal below, connect to the target VM at the echo server’s TCP port number 7. To close the connection, press the &lt;strong&gt;CTRL + ]&lt;/strong&gt; keys simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@TryHackMe$ telnet MACHINE_IP 7
telnet MACHINE_IP 7
Trying MACHINE_IP...
Connected to MACHINE_IP.
Escape character is &amp;#39;^]&amp;#39;.
Hi
Hi
How are you?
How are you?
Bye
Bye
^]

telnet&amp;gt; quit
Connection closed.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the terminal below, we use telnet to connect to the daytime server listening at port 13. We noticed that the connection closes once the current date and time are returned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@TryHackMe$ telnet MACHINE_IP 13
Trying MACHINE_IP...
Connected to MACHINE_IP.
Escape character is &amp;#39;^]&amp;#39;.
Thu Jun 20 12:36:32 PM UTC 2024
Connection closed by foreign host.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s request a web page using telnet. After connecting to port 80, you need to issue the command GET / HTTP/1.1 and identify the host where anything goes, such as Host: telnet.thm. The output below shows the exchange. (The page has been redacted.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: You may have to press Enter after sending the information in case you don’t get a response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@TryHackMe$ telnet MACHINE_IP 80
Trying MACHINE_IP...
Connected to MACHINE_IP.
Escape character is &amp;#39;^]&amp;#39;.
GET / HTTP/1.1
Host: telnet.thm

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html
[...]

Connection closed by foreign h
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to get the flag, as mentioned above the websever listens on port 80, therefore we run &lt;code&gt;telnet MACHINE IP 80&lt;/code&gt; in my case its,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;telnet 10.10.191.138 80
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i got served content content as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt; telnet 10.10.191.138 80
Trying 10.10.191.138...
Connected to 10.10.191.138.
Escape character is &amp;#39;^]&amp;#39;.

HTTP/1.0 400 Bad Request
Content-Type: text/html
Content-Length: 345
Connection: close
Date: Tue, 22 Oct 2024 16:25:09 GMT
Server: *******

&amp;lt;?xml version=&amp;quot;1.0&amp;quot; encoding=&amp;quot;iso-8859-1&amp;quot;?&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html PUBLIC &amp;quot;-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN&amp;quot;
         &amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html xmlns=&amp;quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml&amp;quot; xml:lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot; lang=&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;400 Bad Request&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;400 Bad Request&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;
 &amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
Connection closed by foreign host.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server name and the version  can be seen but the flag is not there, i was having trouple with the connection, then i use curl to obatined the flag.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/networkingconcepts/curl.png&quot; alt=&quot;curl command&quot; /&gt;
&lt;Info&gt; &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; is a command-line tool used to transfer data to or from a server using various protocols, including HTTP, HTTPS, FTP, and more. It allows users to send requests and receive responses, making it useful for testing APIs, downloading files, and performing network diagnostics. With its numerous options, &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; can handle tasks like authentication, data formatting, and custom headers. &lt;/Info&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this room, we covered the ISO OSI and TCP/IP models, comparing and contrasting the two. We also covered IP addresses and subnets, briefly explaining routing. Furthermore, after diving into TCP and UDP, we explained encapsulation. For demonstration purposes, we used telnet to “talk” to different servers over TCP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you have finished Networking Concepts, it is time to join &lt;img src=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/networkingessentials&quot; alt=&quot;Networking Essentials&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>SOC Fundamentals</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/soc-fundemental/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/soc-fundemental/</guid><description>Learn about the SOC team and their processes.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/soc-fundemental/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/soc-fundemental/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Source Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/socfundamentals&quot;&gt;SOC Fundamentals Room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/&quot;&gt;TryHackMe Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Introduction to SOC&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technology has made our lives more efficient, but with this efficiency comes more responsibility. Modern-day fears have evolved from the exploitation of physical assets. The critical data, referred to as &amp;quot;secrets,&amp;quot; are no longer stored in physical files. Organizations now carry vast amounts of confidential data within their networks and systems. Any unauthorized disruption, loss, or modification of this data can result in significant damage. Threat actors continually discover and exploit new vulnerabilities in these networks and systems, posing a major concern in cybersecurity. Traditional security practices may no longer suffice to prevent many of these threats. Therefore, dedicating an entire team to manage your organization’s security is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A SOC (Security Operations Center) is a dedicated facility operated by a specialized security team. This team aims to continuously monitor an organization’s network and resources, identifying suspicious activity to prevent damage. They work 24 hours a day, seven days a week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This room will delve into some key concepts of SOC, one of the most important fields in defensive security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a baseline for SOC (Security Operations Center)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detection and response in SOC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The role of People, Processes, and Technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practical exercise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Purpose and Components of the SOC Team&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main focus of the SOC team is to keep Detection and Response intact. The SOC team has some resources available in the form of security solutions that help them achieve this. These solutions integrate the whole company’s network and all the systems to monitor them from one centralized location. Continuous monitoring is required to detect and respond to any security incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main Focus of SOC: Detect and Respond&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Detection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detect Vulnerabilities&lt;/strong&gt;: 
A vulnerability is a weakness that an attacker can exploit to carry out actions beyond their permission level. Vulnerabilities can be found in any device’s software (operating systems and programs), such as servers or computers. For instance, the SOC might discover that a set of MS Windows computers needs to be patched against a specific published vulnerability. Strictly speaking, vulnerabilities are not necessarily the SOC’s responsibility; however, unfixed vulnerabilities affect the security level of the entire company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detect Unauthorized Activity&lt;/strong&gt;: 
Consider the case where an attacker discovers the username and password of one of the employees and uses them to log in to the company system. It is crucial to detect this kind of unauthorized activity quickly before it causes any damage. Many clues, such as geographic location, can help in detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detect Policy Violations&lt;/strong&gt;: 
A security policy is a set of rules and procedures created to help protect a company against security threats and ensure compliance. What is considered a violation can vary from company to company; examples include downloading pirated media files and sending confidential company files insecurely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detect Intrusions&lt;/strong&gt;: 
Intrusions refer to unauthorized access to systems and networks. One scenario could involve an attacker successfully exploiting a web application. Another might be a user visiting a malicious site and getting their computer infected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Response&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support with Incident Response&lt;/strong&gt;: 
Once an incident is detected, certain steps are taken to respond to it. This response includes minimizing its impact and performing a root cause analysis of the incident. The SOC team also assists the incident response team in carrying out these steps.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/soc.png&quot; alt=&quot;soc&quot;&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Three Pillars of a SOC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these pillars, a SOC team becomes mature and efficiently detects and responds to different incidents. The pillars are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/soc-pillars.png&quot; alt=&quot;soc pillars&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Process&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People, Process, and Technology coexist in a SOC environment. A team of professional individuals working on state-of-the-art security tools within the framework of proper processes creates a mature SOC environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the upcoming tasks, we will discuss each of these pillars individually and examine their importance in the SOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;People in the SOC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the evolution of automating the majority of security tasks, the People in a SOC will always be important. A security solution can generate numerous red flags in a SOC environment, creating significant noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine being part of a fire brigade team with centralized software where all the city’s fire alarms are integrated. Suppose you receive many fire notifications simultaneously for different locations. Upon arrival, your team discovers that most were triggered by excessive smoke from cooking. Ultimately, all efforts would be wasted in addressing non-issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a SOC, relying solely on security solutions without human intervention may lead to a focus on irrelevant problems. It is the People who help security solutions identify genuinely harmful activities and enable a prompt response.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/people.png&quot; alt=&quot;people&quot;&gt;
The People are known as the SOC team, which has the following roles and responsibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Hierarchy of the SOC Team&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOC Analyst (Level 1)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These analysts are the first responders to any detection. Anything detected by the security solution passes through them first. Level 1 Analysts perform basic alert triage to determine if a specific detection is harmful and report these detections through proper channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOC Analyst (Level 2)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While Level 1 handles initial analysis, some detections may require deeper investigation. Level 2 Analysts assist in conducting thorough investigations and correlating data from multiple sources for proper analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOC Analyst (Level 3)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Level 3 Analysts are experienced professionals who proactively search for threat indicators and support incident response activities. Critical severity detections reported by Level 1 and Level 2 Analysts often require detailed responses, including containment, eradication, and recovery, where Level 3 analysts’ experience is invaluable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All analysts work with security solutions that require deployment and configuration. Security Engineers are responsible for deploying and configuring these security solutions to ensure their smooth operation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detection Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security rules are the logic built behind security solutions to detect harmful activities. Level 2 and Level 3 Analysts often create these rules, while the SOC team may also utilize the Detection Engineer role independently for this responsibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOC Manager&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The SOC Manager oversees the processes the SOC team follows and provides support. They also maintain contact with the organization’s CISO (Chief Information Security Officer) to keep them updated on the SOC team’s current security posture and efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The roles in the SOC team can increase or decrease depending on the size and criticality of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process in the SOC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed the roles and responsibilities of different individuals working in the SOC team. Each role has its own processes, as illustrated by the Level 1 SOC Analysts, who are the first responders responsible for alert triage and determining the harm level of alerts. Let’s discuss some important processes involved in a SOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Alert Triage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/questions.png&quot; alt=&quot;soc pillars&quot;&gt;
The alert triage is the foundation of the SOC team. The first response to any alert is to perform triage, which focuses on analyzing the specific alert to determine its severity and prioritize it. The alert triage process revolves around answering the 5 Ws. What are these 5 Ws?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The 5 Ws of SOC&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the triage of an alert, the following questions need to be answered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alert&lt;/strong&gt;: Malware detected on Host: GEORGE PC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;5 Ws&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Answers&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;What?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A malicious file was detected on one of the hosts inside the organization’s network.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;When?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The file was detected at 13:20 on June 5, 2024.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Where?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The file was detected in the directory of the host: &amp;quot;GEORGE PC&amp;quot;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Who?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The file was detected for the user George.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Why?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;After investigation, it was found that the file was downloaded from a pirated software-selling website. The user revealed they downloaded it to use the software for free.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reporting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detected harmful alerts need to be escalated to higher-level analysts for timely response and resolution. These alerts are escalated as tickets and assigned to the relevant personnel. The report should discuss all the 5 Ws, along with a thorough analysis, and should include screenshots as evidence of the activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Incident Response and Forensics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, reported detections indicate highly malicious activities that are critical. In these scenarios, high-level teams initiate an incident response. The incident response process is discussed in detail in the Incident Response room. Occasionally, a detailed forensics activity also needs to be performed. This forensic activity aims to determine the incident’s root cause by analyzing the artifacts from a system or network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Technology in the SOC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having the right People and Processes in place is never enough without security solutions for detection and response. The Technology portion in the SOC pillars refers to the security solutions that efficiently minimize the SOC team&amp;#39;s manual effort to detect and respond to threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An organization’s network consists of many devices and applications. As a security team, individually detecting and responding to threats on each device or application would require significant effort and resources. Security solutions centralize all information from the devices or applications present in the network and automate the detection and response capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s briefly understand some of these security solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;SIEM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security Information and Event Management (SIEM)&lt;/strong&gt; is a popular tool used in almost every SOC environment. This tool collects logs from various network devices, known as log sources. Detection rules are configured in the SIEM solution, containing the logic to identify suspicious activity. The SIEM solution provides detections after correlating them with multiple log sources and alerts us if there’s a match with any of the rules. Modern SIEM solutions go beyond rule-based detection, offering user behavior analytics and threat intelligence capabilities, supported by machine learning algorithms to enhance detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The SIEM solution primarily provides detection capabilities in a SOC environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;EDR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Endpoint Detection and Response (EDR)&lt;/strong&gt; provides the SOC team with detailed real-time and historical visibility of device activities. It operates at the endpoint level and can execute automated responses. EDR has extensive detection capabilities for endpoints, enabling in-depth investigation and quick responses with just a few clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Firewall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;firewall&lt;/strong&gt; serves as a network security barrier, acting as a gatekeeper between internal networks and external ones (such as the Internet). It monitors incoming and outgoing network traffic, filtering unauthorized traffic. The firewall also deploys detection rules to identify and block suspicious traffic before it reaches the internal network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several other security solutions play unique roles in a SOC environment, such as Antivirus, EPP, IDS/IPS, XDR, SOAR, and more. The decision on what technology to deploy in the SOC comes after careful consideration of the threat surface and the resources available within the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Practical Exercise of SOC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This practical exercise utilizes People, Processes, and Technology to provide a walkthrough of the role of a Level 1 Analyst in the SOC team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the &lt;strong&gt;View Site&lt;/strong&gt; button below to display the lab on the right side of the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scenario&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are the Level 1 Analyst of your organization’s SOC team. You receive an alert indicating that port scanning activity has been observed on one of the hosts in the network. You have access to the SIEM solution, where you can view all the associated logs for this alert. Your task is to examine the logs individually and answer the questions related to the 5 Ws given below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: The vulnerability assessment team has notified the SOC team that they were running a port scan activity inside the network from the host: &lt;strong&gt;10.0.0.8&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/Cyber-Security-101/dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;soc pillars&quot;&gt;
Based on the above picture, we can answer some of the questions below. We will be working with an alert that has not been resolved. In the above picture, we can see an ACKNOWLEDGE button, which we can use to take ownership of the alert. After that, we can click on Investigate in the SIEM to begin the alert analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Explanation of the SIEM Log Traffic Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SIEM log traffic table provides a detailed view of network activity related to a specific alert. Here’s a breakdown of each column and what the data represents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Column&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The date and time when the log entry was recorded (e.g., June 12, 2024 17:24).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Log Type&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The type of log entry, indicating that this is traffic data (e.g., Traffic).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Range&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The type of network (e.g., Private) from which the traffic originated.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source IP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The IP address of the device that generated the traffic (e.g., 10.0.0.8).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Destination IP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The IP address of the device receiving the traffic (e.g., 10.0.0.3).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Port&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The port number used by the source device to send traffic (e.g., 56927).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Destination Port&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The port number on the destination device that received the traffic (e.g., 443).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Source Host Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The name of the source device (e.g., NESSUS), which is often a tool used for scanning.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Destination Host Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The name of the destination device (e.g., JOE PC) that received the traffic.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Insights from the Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port Scanning Activity&lt;/strong&gt;: The logs show multiple connections from the source IP (10.0.0.8) to the destination IP (10.0.0.3) on various ports, indicating a potential port scanning activity.
After completing your analysis, click on the Complete button above to obtain your flag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This room helped us learn some exciting facts about the SOC team. We saw its responsibilities and the pillars, People, Process, and Technology, that mature any SOC environment. This room focused on understanding how People, Processes, and Technology play their roles in the day-to-day SOC use cases. Lastly, we got our hands on a practice lab and solved a real-world SOC alert as a level 1 Analyst&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The SOC Fundamentals room provided a comprehensive introduction to the essential components of a Security Operations Center. It emphasized the critical role that SOC teams play in safeguarding an organization’s digital assets. With the increasing sophistication of cyber threats, the necessity for a dedicated team to monitor, detect, and respond to security incidents has never been clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion around the three pillars of a SOC—People, Processes, and Technology—was particularly insightful. Each pillar is interdependent and essential for creating a mature and effective SOC environment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People&lt;/strong&gt;: The SOC team is the backbone of the operation. Each member has specific roles that contribute to the overall security posture of the organization. The hierarchy from Level 1 to Level 3 Analysts, along with Engineers and Managers, highlights the collaborative effort required in threat detection and response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processes&lt;/strong&gt;: The structured processes for alert triage, reporting, and incident response are crucial for efficiently handling security incidents. Understanding the 5 Ws during alert triage helps in prioritizing and addressing threats effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology&lt;/strong&gt;: The tools and solutions like SIEM, EDR, and firewalls play a vital role in automating detection and response. They enable the SOC team to focus on genuine threats rather than getting bogged down by noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this room not only enhanced my understanding of SOC functions but also provided practical insights through a hands-on lab experience, simulating real-world scenarios as a Level 1 Analyst. This approach solidified the theoretical concepts learned and highlighted the importance of teamwork and structured processes in cybersecurity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Day 1 - Introduction to Packet Tracer</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/introtopacket-tracer/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/introtopacket-tracer/</guid><description>Overview of Cisco Packet Tracer and setting up a basic DHCP example</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/introtopacket-tracer/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/introtopacket-tracer/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction to Cisco Packet Tracer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cisco Packet Tracer is a powerful network simulation tool used for building, configuring, and troubleshooting network topologies. This tool allows you to visualize networking concepts in a hands-on manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this lab, we will introduce the following objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding the Packet Tracer interface.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning about commonly used devices in Packet Tracer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up a basic DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol) example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Info&gt;
  In Day 1, we cover the basics of Cisco Packet Tracer, including its interface and key features.
&lt;/Info&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a detailed table explaining the different types of cables used in Packet Tracer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cable Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Length&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandwidth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copper Straight-Through&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 100 meters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100 Mbps to 1 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for connecting devices to switches or routers (e.g., PC to Switch, Router to Switch).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copper Crossover&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 100 meters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100 Mbps to 1 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used to connect similar devices (e.g., Switch to Switch, PC to PC, Router to Router).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiber Optic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 100 km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Gbps to 100 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for long-distance, high-bandwidth connections (e.g., between data centers, switches in different locations).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serial Cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Variable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5 Mbps to 45 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for WAN connections between routers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coaxial Cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 500 meters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used in older Ethernet (10BASE2, 10BASE5) configurations and some broadband applications.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Console Cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for device configuration, typically connects to a router or switch&amp;#39;s console port for CLI access.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiber Optic Multimode&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 2 km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Gbps to 10 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for shorter distances with high bandwidth (e.g., within a building or campus).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiber Optic Single-mode&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 100 km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 Gbps to 100 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for long-distance communication with minimal loss.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethernet Cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 to 100 meters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10 Mbps to 10 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for general networking purposes in homes, offices, and data centers (e.g., PC to Switch, Switch to Router).&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB Cable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Variable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 480 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used to connect external devices such as USB storage, printers, and out-of-band router/switch management.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Overview of Interfaces Used in Packet Tracer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Cisco Packet Tracer, different types of interfaces are used to connect devices. Each interface type has specific characteristics such as bandwidth, port type, and application. Understanding these interfaces helps in configuring networks correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a detailed table explaining the different types of interfaces used in Packet Tracer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interface Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Port Type&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bandwidth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Application&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast Ethernet (Fa0/1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RJ-45 (Copper)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;100 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Standard Ethernet for LAN connections between devices such as switches, routers, and PCs.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gigabit Ethernet (Gi0/1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RJ-45 (Copper)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;High-speed Ethernet for large LAN or small WAN connections.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Serial (S0/0/0)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Serial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5 Mbps to 45 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WAN connectivity, typically used for point-to-point links between routers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fiber (F0/1)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fiber Optic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 Gbps to 100 Gbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;High-speed data transmission over long distances between switches or routers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VLAN Interface&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virtual&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Depends on underlying physical connection&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logical interface for Virtual LANs (VLANs), used to segment network traffic.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Console (CON)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RJ-45 (Console Port)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides device management access for CLI configuration.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Auxiliary (AUX)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RJ-45 (Aux Port)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for remote access over a modem connection to manage routers or switches.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless (Wi-Fi)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Wireless Radio&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Varies (54 Mbps to 1 Gbps)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Provides wireless network connectivity between access points and wireless devices like PCs or laptops.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loopback Interface&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Virtual&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;NA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Used for testing and management purposes; often used as a static IP on routers.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;USB Interface&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Up to 480 Mbps&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Connects external devices for data transfer, out-of-band management, or firmware upgrades.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Main Features of Packet Tracer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Packet Tracer offers several features for beginners and professionals alike:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simulation of Networking Concepts&lt;/strong&gt;: Create a variety of network configurations to simulate real-world scenarios.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interactive Interface&lt;/strong&gt;: The drag-and-drop interface allows easy addition and connection of devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Device Support&lt;/strong&gt;: Includes various Cisco devices like routers, switches, and access points for practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Real-Time and Simulation Modes&lt;/strong&gt;: Run your network in real-time or switch to simulation mode to observe data packets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support for Multiple Protocols&lt;/strong&gt;: Learn about different networking technologies, including DHCP, OSPF, and RIP.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Resources&lt;/strong&gt;: Built-in tutorials and labs help you learn networking concepts effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commonly Used Devices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will frequently work with the following devices in Packet Tracer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Routers&lt;/strong&gt;: Connect different networks and direct data packets (e.g., Cisco 7200, 1941).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Switches&lt;/strong&gt;: Connect devices within a single network (e.g., Cisco 2960, 3560).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End Devices&lt;/strong&gt;: PCs, laptops, and servers that send and receive data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Points&lt;/strong&gt;: Enable wireless connectivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting Up a Basic DHCP Example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steps&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Packet Tracer&lt;/strong&gt;: Launch the application and create a new project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add Devices&lt;/strong&gt;: Drag a router, a switch, and two PCs onto the workspace.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connect Devices&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the router to the switch using a straight-through cable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect each PC to the switch using straight-through cables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configure the Router&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on the router and select the CLI tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter the following commands to enable DHCP:&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;enable
configure terminal
ip dhcp pool MYPOOL
network 192.168.1.0 255.255.255.0
default-router 192.168.1.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configure the PCs&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on each PC, go to the Desktop tab, and select IP Configuration. Choose &amp;quot;DHCP&amp;quot; to obtain an IP address automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test the Configuration&lt;/strong&gt;: Use the command prompt in the PCs to ping each other and verify the DHCP configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/Day-1.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;Packet Tracer Interface&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, you learned the basics of Cisco Packet Tracer, its main features, and how to set up a simple DHCP example. Understanding these fundamentals will help you as you progress through the rest of the labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to explore Packet Tracer further and experiment with different configurations!
{/* 
&lt;a href=&quot;your-video-link-here&quot;&gt;Watch the Day 1 Video&lt;/a&gt;  Day-1.PNG&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;your-lab-configuration-link-here&quot;&gt;Packet Tracer Lab Configuration File&lt;/a&gt; */}&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>IR Playbooks</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/ir-playbook/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/ir-playbook/</guid><description>Learn the basics of creating and using IR playbooks.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/ir-playbook/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/ir-playbook/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing what actions to take in case a specific alert is triggered can often become confusing when dealing with alerts in a SOC. Incident Response (IR) playbooks help reduce some of the confusion arising from such scenarios. But what are IR playbooks, and how do you create them? Let&amp;#39;s learn in this room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Objectives&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this room, we will be able to answer the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are IR playbooks, and how are they used?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we capture the different steps of the IR process in a playbook?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What roles and responsibilities are assigned to the different members of the SOC in a playbook?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before starting this room, please ensure that you have completed the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/introtoirandim&quot;&gt;Intro to IR and IM room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/module/incident-response&quot;&gt;Incident Response Module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/advancedelkqueries&quot;&gt;Advanced ELK Queries room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Incident Response Documentation Universe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As organizations mature, they document the scenarios and steps that personnel should take in their daily work. In a mature SOC, processes govern the response to alerts, defining roles and responsibilities for monitoring incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Incident Response Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Incident Response (IR) process is crucial for incident management. While this process varies across organizations, key components typically include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A RACI matrix defining roles and responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An escalation matrix for communication to management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A severity matrix for classifying incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Procedures for handling cybersecurity crises.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process ensures that organizations are prepared to respond to incidents without ambiguity, although crises may necessitate deviations from established procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Need for Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite having an IR process, playbooks are essential for providing detailed, granular steps for different types of incidents. The IR process outlines high-level steps but lacks specifics. Playbooks clarify what actions to take during each phase of an incident, preventing conflicts about response actions.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/ir/ir-tree.png&quot; alt=&quot;Incident response process&quot;&gt;
Each incident type—such as phishing, malware, account compromise, and ransomware—should have a dedicated playbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use Cases and Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a SOC, use cases are developed to flag suspicious activity from terabytes of logs. Each use case requires a corresponding playbook, although multiple use cases may trigger a single playbook. This creates a one-to-many mapping.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/ir/phising_playbook.png&quot; alt=&quot;playbook phishing&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Automating Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playbooks contain repeatable steps that can often be automated. Using a SOAR platform, SOC teams can automate parts of playbooks, easing the workload on analysts. The degree of automation varies by organization, but well-defined playbooks pave the way for automation and reduce alert fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating playbooks and use cases simplifies analysts&amp;#39; tasks, ensuring consistent SOC output and minimizing ambiguity. This structured approach also reveals opportunities for automating repetitive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the upcoming tasks, we will explore how to effectively follow and create playbooks as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;IR Process and Playbooks: Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playbooks are designed to align with the Incident Response (IR) process, starting with the preparation phase. While many organizations do not include preparation in their playbooks—since it occurs before an incident is detected—it is crucial for playbook development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preparation ensures that the capability to detect, investigate, and respond to incidents is established. Although this phase is often overlooked in playbooks, it is typically mentioned in the prerequisites section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Prerequisites of Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before creating a playbook, several prerequisites must be met to ensure effective incident response. Key points to verify include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All relevant logs must be present and integrated into the SIEM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logs should be properly parsed, with required fields extracted and searchable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logs need to contain essential fields (e.g., machine information, IP information).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use cases must be established to flag specific behaviors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recommended security controls should align with the organization’s policies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example Prerequisites for Specific Playbooks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Phishing Playbook Prerequisites&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevant Logs:&lt;/strong&gt; Email gateway logs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required Fields:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email recipient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Email sender&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subject&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URLs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attachment names and hashes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;QR codes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Use Cases:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Known malicious file hashes in attachments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious file extensions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious sender domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credential harvesting URLs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended Security Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Block email&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quarantine suspicious attachments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete email from inbox&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Malware Playbook Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevant Logs:&lt;/strong&gt; EDR logs, Sysmon logs, Syslog, Windows event logs, network communication logs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required Fields:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Parent process names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process ID&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;File/process hashes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Command line parameters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Use Cases:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious parent-child relationships&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious file access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious registry events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recommended Security Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Malware quarantine in EDR&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shellcode blocking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exploit prevention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These prerequisites may vary based on organizational requirements but typically follow a similar structure, including additional security policies as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What stage of the IR process can be translated into prerequisites for the playbooks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;preparation&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;IR Process and Playbooks: Detection and Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once an incident is triggered, the detection and analysis phase of the Incident Response (IR) process begins. Playbooks provide detailed steps to verify incidents during this phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Workflow Diagrams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playbooks often include workflow diagrams to clarify the process. These diagrams serve as a foundation for further detailing the steps in each playbook.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/ir/diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;Workflow Diagrams&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Detection and Analysis Checklist&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key points to consider during detection and analysis include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alert trigger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial verification of log data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verification of potential Indicators of Compromise (IOCs) using OSINT and threat intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analysis of IOC metadata (e.g., parent process, command line instructions)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depending on findings, either close the incident or escalate it for further action.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example from Phishing Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Detection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phishing playbook can be triggered by alerts from the SIEM or user-reported emails. Common triggers include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails from newly created domains&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails with known malicious links&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails with suspicious attachment types&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emails from domains with bad reputations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon triggering the playbook, the analyst will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify sender and recipient(s).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build context from the email subject and body.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determine the sender&amp;#39;s IP address and domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract URLs and attachments, checking any QR codes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consult threat intelligence sources for reputation checks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verify extracted items against platforms like VirusTotal for malicious flags.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check for signs of credential phishing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate suspicious logins from email recipients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If identified as phishing, escalate; otherwise, close the incident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example from Malware Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Detection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The malware playbook can be triggered by alerts such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;EDR marking a process as malicious&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suspicious files executing from temporary directories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scripts running from browsers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The analyst will follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the process that triggered the alert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the process&amp;#39;s hash on threat intelligence platforms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verify if the process is clean or malicious, noting not to upload binaries without management approval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze any executed files linked to the process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investigate the parent process of the triggering process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examine network logs for suspicious downloads or phishing emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If phishing is involved, trigger the phishing playbook.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Execute the malware in a secure sandbox to study its behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document malware activities for future reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preserve evidence of malicious activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct forensic analysis to identify further IOCs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform organization-wide threat hunting for affected systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these findings, the analyst will either close the incident if it&amp;#39;s a False Positive or escalate if it’s a True Positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What steps should we follow if the incident is a False Positive?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;close incident&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;IR Process and Playbooks: Containment, Eradication, and Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After analyzing an incident, the analyst decides whether to close it as a False Positive or escalate it as a True Positive needing action. If it’s a True Positive, further steps for containment, eradication, and recovery are initiated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Escalation Process&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typically, an L1 analyst handles initial identification and analysis. If the incident is a False Positive, it is closed. If it’s a True Positive, it gets escalated to an L2 analyst, who will work on containment, eradication, and recovery, often with help from an L3 analyst for advanced analysis. The L3 analyst also manages and updates playbooks as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Checklist for Containment, Eradication, and Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These steps are followed only when an incident is confirmed as a True Positive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the root cause of the incident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess the impact and affected assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contain the threat by isolating affected assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the threat&amp;#39;s impact from affected assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restore assets to the last known good configuration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resume normal services for all affected assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example From Phishing Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Containment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once a phishing email is confirmed as a True Positive, the following actions should be taken:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extract artifacts from the phishing email (e.g., IP addresses, file hashes).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Block the sender’s email, domain, and IP on the email gateway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Block file hashes on the EDR.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prevent access to phishing links via the web proxy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Eradication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If users interacted with the phishing email, additional steps include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove phishing emails from all affected users&amp;#39; inboxes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isolate machines of users who clicked on links or downloaded attachments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revoke active sessions and reset credentials as needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To restore normal operations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset credentials for affected accounts and ensure MFA is enabled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audit user account activities and revert any malicious actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reimage machines affected by malicious attachments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example From Malware Playbook&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Containment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For malware incidents, the containment steps include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Isolate affected systems from the network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revoke sessions of logged-in accounts on these systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Block communication with potential command-and-control servers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Eradication&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To eradicate malware, follow these steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shut down services associated with the malicious process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the malicious binary from affected systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run a complete EDR scan to ensure removal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reimage affected systems if necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reset credentials for affected accounts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For recovery after malware eradication:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable MFA on affected accounts and enforce strong password policies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Audit the malware&amp;#39;s activities and revert any unauthorized changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restore affected machines to their last known good configuration and resume services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the phases of containment, eradication, and recovery often overlap and can be grouped together in the IR process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To recover systems affected by an incident, which configuration should we bring them back to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;last known good configuration&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;IR Process and Playbooks: Post-Incident Activity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-incident activity is the final stage of the Incident Response (IR) process, focusing on understanding and improving from the incident. The steps taken in this phase depend on the specific incident and the gaps identified during the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Questions Addressed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During post-incident activity, the following questions are explored:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why did the incident occur?&lt;/strong&gt; This often involves using the &amp;quot;5 Whys&amp;quot; method to reach the root cause.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What gaps were identified?&lt;/strong&gt; Understanding what could have been improved to prevent the incident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we enhance People, Processes, and Technology?&lt;/strong&gt; Finding ways to avoid similar incidents in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What actions could have minimized the incident&amp;#39;s impact?&lt;/strong&gt; Reflecting on preventative measures that could have been taken.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Subjectivity of Post-Incident Activity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach to post-incident activities can vary significantly based on organizational dynamics, the type of incident, its impact, and the findings from the investigation. Therefore, specific steps for this phase are typically not included in playbooks. Instead, broad guidelines are outlined in the IR plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Guidelines Based on Severity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope and guidelines for post-incident activities often depend on the severity and impact of the incident. Many or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the last stage of the IR process?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;post-activity incident&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/tryhackme/ir/post-inctivity.png&quot; alt=&quot;Workflow Diagrams&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Forensic Imaging</title><link>https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/forensic-imaging/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://frosti.saroprock.com/blog/forensic-imaging/</guid><description>Learn the basic concepts of forensic imaging.</description><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;This rendering was automatically generated by Frosti Feed and may have formatting issues. For the best experience, please visit:&lt;a href=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/forensic-imaging/&quot;&gt;https://frosti.saroprock.com//blog/forensic-imaging/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;import Collapse from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Collapse.astro&amp;quot;;
import Diff from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Diff.astro&amp;quot;;
import Error from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Error.astro&amp;quot;;
import Info from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Info.astro&amp;quot;;
import Kbd from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Kbd.astro&amp;quot;;
import Success from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Success.astro&amp;quot;;
import Warning from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/Warning.astro&amp;quot;;
import TimeLine from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/TimeLine.astro&amp;quot;;
import LinkCard from &amp;quot;../../components/mdx/LinkCard.astro&amp;quot;;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Digital Forensics, imaging involves creating an exact, bit-by-bit copy of digital storage media. This captures all data, including deleted and hidden files, while preserving the original data for thorough examination. The main goal is to create a verifiable copy for investigations and legal proceedings, ensuring the integrity of digital evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process is essential for maintaining the chain of custody by documenting the handling of digital evidence, demonstrating that the data has been preserved and not tampered with, which is critical for legal transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learning Objectives&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand the basics of the forensic imaging process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explore different environment settings for imaging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn how to create a raw image from an attached device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perform an integrity check of an image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/introdigitalforensics&quot;&gt;Intro to Digital Forensics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/introductoryroomdfirmodule&quot;&gt;DFIR: An Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/linuxfundamentalspart1&quot;&gt;Linux Fundamentals 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/dfirprocesslegalconsiderations&quot;&gt;Legal Considerations in DFIR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start imaging a disk, you need to find the drive you want to copy and prepare it for the process. This involves making a duplicate of the drive&amp;#39;s data and checking that the copy is accurate. It’s crucial to do this in a way that keeps track of all actions taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different operating systems have different ways of handling files, so you need the right tools for each. In this case, we’ll be using Linux to create the copy of the drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Write-Blockers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Devices that prevent modifications to data on physical disks during analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure that data can be read without altering original evidence by intercepting write commands between the disk and the OS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Audit Trail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A chronological record of actions and events within a system for accountability and security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documents each step for traceability, adaptable to legal or compliance requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Actions can be recorded manually or automatically, helping to preserve evidence and track activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we are using &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;bash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;history&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; command can help us log our activity. It can be saved using a timestamp and preserved in a file. Below, we can observe a chart with some commands recommended to use during our session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Command&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;set -o history&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enables command history in the shell, allowing it to record the commands you enter.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;shopt -s histappend&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ensures that the command history is appended to the history file instead of overwriting it when exiting.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTCONTROL=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clears any settings that control which commands are saved in the history, ensuring all commands are recorded.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTIGNORE=&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Clears any settings that ignore specific patterns of commands, so all commands are saved in the history.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTFILE=~/.bash_history&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sets the file where the command history is saved.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTFILESIZE=-1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sets no limit on the number of lines stored in the history file.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTSIZE=-1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Sets no limit on the number of commands retained in the shell history.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;export HISTTIMEFORMAT=&amp;quot;%F-%R &amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Formats timestamps in the history as &amp;quot;YYYY-MM-DD HH&amp;quot; for each command.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another good practice is to log all sessions. This could be achieved with bash internals, but other easy-to-use software can achieve the same, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man1/script.1.html&quot;&gt;script&lt;/a&gt;, a UNIX tool present in several Linux distributions, or similar tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mjording/ttyrec&quot;&gt;ttyrec&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Accessing the File System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The method for accessing the file system is similar for all disks—whether they are physically or virtually attached to a Linux OS. After setting up your environment and logging your actions, you can use the df command to view the attached devices on the target machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Filesystem Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ df
Filesystem     1K-blocks    Used Available Use% Mounted on
/dev/root       40581564 7240136  33325044  18% /
devtmpfs          995480       0    995480   0% /dev
tmpfs            1003808       0   1003808   0% /dev/shm
tmpfs             200764    1148    199616   1% /run
tmpfs               5120       0      5120   0% /run/lock
tmpfs            1003808       0   1003808   0% /sys/fs/cgroup
/dev/loop0         25600   25600         0 100% /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/7628
/dev/loop1         25856   25856         0 100% /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/7993
/dev/loop2        108032  108032         0 100% /snap/core/16574
/dev/loop3        106752  106752         0 100% /snap/core/17200
/dev/loop4         57088   57088         0 100% /snap/core18/2812
/dev/loop5         57088   57088         0 100% /snap/core18/2829
/dev/loop6         65536   65536         0 100% /snap/core20/2105
/dev/loop7         65536   65536         0 100% /snap/core20/2318
/dev/loop8         69632   69632         0 100% /snap/lxd/22526
/dev/loop9         94080   94080         0 100% /snap/lxd/24061
tmpfs             200760       0    200760   0% /run/user/1000
tmpfs             200760       8    200752   1% /run/user/114
tmpfs             200760       4    200756   1% /run/user/1001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drives are attached as devices under the /dev directory. In the output above, the current disk used by the OS is listed under /dev/root. Our device is not mounted yet, and since it is a Virtual Disk attached to a loop interface, it will not appear using the command df. This is also common for physical disks when not directly attached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can still list block devices using the lsblk command with the -a option to list all devices, as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Forensic Imaging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ sudo dc3dd if=/dev/loop10 of=example1.img log=imaging_loop10.txt

dc3dd 7.2.646 started at 2024-06-28 22:58:59 +0000
compiled options:
command line: dc3dd if=/dev/loop10 of=example1.img log=imaging_loop10.txt
device size: 2252800 sectors (probed),    1,153,433,600 bytes
sector size: 512 bytes (probed)
  1153433600 bytes ( 1.1 G ) copied ( 100% ),   13 s, 84 M/s                  

input results for device `/dev/loop10&amp;#39;:
   2252800 sectors in
   0 bad sectors replaced by zeros

output results for file `example1.img&amp;#39;:
   2252800 sectors out

dc3dd completed at 2024-06-28 22:59:12 +0000

The output from the lsblk -a command shows several loop interfaces and their details. Notably, loop10 is initialized with 1.1 GB, which matches the disk size needed for creating images. It&amp;#39;s important to ensure there&amp;#39;s enough space on the destination disk, which is xvda (40 GB, mounted at /).

To gather more information about the devices, you can use the losetup -l command to list the devices and their assigned paths, such as /dev/loop10.


user@tryhackme$ sudo losetup -l /dev/loop10
NAME        SIZELIMIT OFFSET AUTOCLEAR RO BACK-FILE                 DIO LOG-SEC
/dev/loop10         0      0         0  0 /home/ubuntu/example1.img   0     512
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to acquire further information like the UUID of the image using the blkid with the interface as an argument, as demonstrated in the following example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ sudo blkid /dev/loop10
/dev/loop10: UUID=&amp;quot;1895de04-f9ee-4b8b-b49d-9ef55770073c&amp;quot; TYPE=&amp;quot;ext4&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the information above logged into our notes, we should proceed to create the disk&amp;#39;s image. Note that if we were using a physical disk, we could also use commands like hparn to get information about the manufacturer, serial number, and other required data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What command can be used to list all block devices in Linux OS?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;lsblk&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Which bash command displays all commands executed in a session?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;History&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Creating a Forensic Image&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Now that we have identified the device, we want to create an image. Let&amp;#39;s go ahead and copy this disk to a raw image file for further inspection. This could also be done to another disk if needed, which is a common practice, but in this case, we will do it to a local file in our system with the .img extension to identify the file as an image&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As we recall from our previous task, there is a great variety of tools we can use to create images. We will use dc3dd in this example, an enhanced version of the UNIX command dd. Below, you can find a list of some common tools used to create images&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Tool&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Standard Unix utility for copying and converting files,used for raw disk images&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;dc3dd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enhanced version of &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; with forensic features like hashing and logging&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;ddrescue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data recovery tool that copies data from damaged drives efficiently&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;FTK Imager&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;GUI-based tool for easy creation of forensic images with comprehensive features&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;Guymager&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;GUI forensic imaging tool that supports multiple formats and detailed logging&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;EWF tools&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tools for creating and managing Expert Witness Format (EWF) images in digital forensics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;To image a device with dc3dd:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;green&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;if=/dev/loop10 &lt;/span&gt; for the input device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;green&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;of=example1.img &lt;/span&gt; for the output file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;green&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;log=imaging_loop10.txt &lt;/span&gt; to save output logs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below, we can observe the command output of dc3dd using the parameters mentioned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ sudo dc3dd if=/dev/loop10 of=example1.img log=imaging_loop10.txt

dc3dd 7.2.646 started at 2024-06-28 22:58:59 +0000
compiled options:
command line: dc3dd if=/dev/loop10 of=example1.img log=imaging_loop10.txt
device size: 2252800 sectors (probed),    1,153,433,600 bytes
sector size: 512 bytes (probed)
  1153433600 bytes ( 1.1 G ) copied ( 100% ),   13 s, 84 M/s                  

input results for device `/dev/loop10&amp;#39;:
   2252800 sectors in
   0 bad sectors replaced by zeros

output results for file `example1.img&amp;#39;:
   2252800 sectors out

dc3dd completed at 2024-06-28 22:59:12 +0000
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the output above, we can confirm that the operation seemed to be successful and that we created a file of the same size, as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ ls -alh example1.img 
-rw-r--r-- 1 root root 1.1G Jun 28 22:28 example1.img
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Integrity Checking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrity checking in digital forensics imaging is vital to ensure that a forensic copy matches the original data. This is done using cryptographic hash functions like MD5, SHA-1, or SHA-256 to generate unique hash values for both the original and copied data. Comparing these hashes confirms that the evidence remains unaltered, which is essential for its reliability in legal contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools like dc3dd can automatically calculate and verify hashes during the imaging process, enhancing assurance. Regular integrity checks throughout the investigation help maintain data integrity and preserve the chain of custody&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ sudo lsblk -l
loop0    7:0    0  26.7M  1 loop /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/5163
loop1    7:1    0  24.9M  1 loop /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/7628
loop2    7:2    0 105.4M  1 loop /snap/core/16574
loop3    7:3    0 104.2M  1 loop /snap/core/17200
loop4    7:4    0  55.7M  1 loop /snap/core18/2812
loop5    7:5    0  55.7M  1 loop /snap/core18/2829
loop6    7:6    0  63.9M  1 loop /snap/core20/2105
loop7    7:7    0    64M  1 loop /snap/core20/2318
loop8    7:8    0  67.9M  1 loop /snap/lxd/22526
loop9    7:9    0  91.9M  1 loop /snap/lxd/24061
loop10   7:10   0   1.1G  0 loop 
loop11   7:11   0   1.1G  0 loop /mnt/example1
xvda   202:0    0    40G  0 disk 
xvda1  202:1    0    40G  0 part /
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can observe that the device is still listed in &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;brown&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;/dev/loop10&lt;/span&gt;  Let&amp;#39;s ensure our imaging process was successful. To do that, let&amp;#39;s calculate the MD5 hash of the image we created, &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;brown&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;example1.img&lt;/span&gt;, and let&amp;#39;s do the same for the &amp;lt;span style={{ color: &amp;#39;brown&amp;#39; }}&amp;gt;device/dev/loop10&lt;/span&gt;. The results should match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ sudo md5sum example1.img 
483ca14c7524b8667974a922662b87e8  example1.img


user@tryhackme$ sudo md5sum /dev/loop10
483ca14c7524b8667974a922662b87e8  /dev/loop10
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown above, the calculated hash indeed matches, passing the integrity check for this image we created. Thus, we can confirm that the imaging process has been successful through hashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;What is the MD5 hash of the image &amp;quot;exercise.img&amp;quot; located in /home/analyst/?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;start the machine in home, -&amp;gt; sudo md5sum exercise.img 
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;1f1da616156f73083521478c334841bb&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other Types of Imaging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that other types of imaging procedures can be performed, not only on disk devices. These can include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Remote Imaging&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Involves creating an image over the network, allowing data acquisition without physical access to the device.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;USB Images&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates an image of a USB drive&amp;#39;s contents.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Docker Images&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Creates a snapshot of a Docker container&amp;#39;s filesystem and configuration.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have an image, we can also verify that the image is working and can be used to inspect it; for that, we could mount the image to verify the process is complete correctly. Let&amp;#39;s go ahead and mount the image we created, example1.img.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we observed before, our disk assigned to the loop interface loop10 is not mounted as the command df displays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;user@tryhackme$ df -h
Filesystem      Size  Used Avail Use% Mounted on
/dev/root        39G  7.9G   31G  21% /
devtmpfs        973M     0  973M   0% /dev
tmpfs           981M     0  981M   0% /dev/shm
tmpfs           197M  1.2M  195M   1% /run
tmpfs           5.0M     0  5.0M   0% /run/lock
tmpfs           981M     0  981M   0% /sys/fs/cgroup
/dev/loop0       27M   27M     0 100% /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/5163
/dev/loop1       25M   25M     0 100% /snap/amazon-ssm-agent/7628
/dev/loop2      106M  106M     0 100% /snap/core/16574
/dev/loop3      105M  105M     0 100% /snap/core/17200
/dev/loop4       56M   56M     0 100% /snap/core18/2812
/dev/loop5       56M   56M     0 100% /snap/core18/2829
/dev/loop6       64M   64M     0 100% /snap/core20/2105
/dev/loop7       64M   64M     0 100% /snap/core20/2318
/dev/loop8       68M   68M     0 100% /snap/lxd/22526
/dev/loop9       92M   92M     0 100% /snap/lxd/24061
tmpfs           197M     0  197M   0% /run/user/1000
tmpfs           197M  8.0K  197M   1% /run/user/114
tmpfs           197M  4.0K  197M   1% /run/user/1001
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s mount it using the mount command
    - First, create a mount point directory /mnt/example1  with the command sudo mkdir -p /mnt/example1
    - Then, use the command sudo mount -o loop example1.img /mnt/example1 to mount the image
    - After that, we can verify by exploring the mount point we created using the ls command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot;&gt;ls /home/practical/
flag.txt  lost+found  testpractical01  testpractical02  testpractical03  testpractical04  testpractical05
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Mount the image &amp;quot;exercise.img&amp;quot; located in the analyst home directory folder. What is the content of the file &amp;quot;flag.txt&amp;quot; located within exercise.img?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;!Mounting](/Frosti/public/main/mount.png)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{/* &lt;details&gt;
  &lt;summary&gt;View Answer&lt;/summary&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;THM{mounttt-mounttt-me}&lt;/Success&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt; */}


&lt;h2&gt;Practical Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Create an image of the attached 1gb loop device. What is the MD5 hash of the image?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://frosti.saroprock.com/main/practical.png&quot; alt=&quot;Practical&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;1fab86e499934dda789c9c4aaf27101d&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Mount the image from the 1 GB loop device. What is the content of the file &amp;quot;flag.txt&amp;quot;?&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in image above
{/* &lt;Collapse title=&quot;View Answer.&quot;&gt;
  &lt;Success&gt;&lt;p&gt;THM{well-done-imaginggggggg}&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/Success&gt;
&lt;/Collapse&gt; */}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this room, we learned the basics of forensic imaging, defining the main concepts and performing tasks that will put us in practical scenarios where we performed imaging of devices, mount, and check their integrity through hashing algorithms.
You can learn more about forensic imaging or more about Linux forensics in the rooms below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/linuxforensics&quot;&gt;Linux Forensics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/linuxfundamentalspart2&quot;&gt;Linux Fundamentals 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tryhackme.com/r/room/linuxlogsinvestigations&quot;&gt;Linux Logs Investigation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><dc:creator>bakeery</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2024 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>